<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Excommunicatio excommunicata, or, A censure of the Presbyterian censures and proceedings in the Classis at Manchester wherein is modestly examined what ecclesiastical or civil function [sic] they pretend for their new and usurped power : in a discourse betwixt the ministers of that Classis, and some dissenting Christians.</title>
            <author>Allen, Isaac, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1026A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875646</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Excommunicatio excommunicata, or, A censure of the Presbyterian censures and proceedings in the Classis at Manchester wherein is modestly examined what ecclesiastical or civil function [sic] they pretend for their new and usurped power : in a discourse betwixt the ministers of that Classis, and some dissenting Christians.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Isaac, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Allen, Isaac, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Heyrick, Richard, 1600-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 55+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Ministers of the Classis" include R. Heyrick and others and "dissenting Christians" include I. Allen and others. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: all after p. 55 lacking; pages torn, and stained. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [10].</note>
                  <note>The word "function" on t.p. has been struck through and replaced in ms. by "sanction".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Excommunicatio Excommunicata.</p>
            <p>OR, A CENSURE OF THE Presbyterian Cenſures And proceedings in the Claſsis at <hi>MANCHESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is modeſtly examined what Eccleſiaſtical or civil Function they pretend for their new and uſurped Power.</p>
            <p>In a Diſcourſe betwixt the Miniſters of that Claſſis, and ſome diſſenting Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Arms in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152166:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152166:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N ſuch an age as this, when the heat of vain and unprofitable controverſies has bred more ſcriblers,<note place="margin">Plautus.</note> than a hot ſummer (in the <hi>Comedians</hi> ſimile) does flies, it might ſeem more rational, according to <hi>Solomons</hi> rule, for prudent men to keep ſilence, then to vex themſelves and diſquiet others with ſuch empty diſcourſes, as rather enlarge then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the differences of Gods people. It was a ſad age, that of <hi>Domitian,</hi> of which the Hiſtorian affirmeth,<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> that then <hi>Inertia pro ſapientiâ erat,</hi> Ignorance was the beſt knowledge, lazineſs and ſervility was the beſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and we could wiſh this age did not too much reſemble that: But when we ſee every <hi>Marſyas</hi> with an old Pipe of <hi>Minerva's,</hi> dares contend with <hi>Apollo;</hi> that men of low and cheap abilities, are too loud and too hard for men of the choiceſt and beſt deſign, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Inertia pro ſapientia erit,</hi> He's the beſt Orator that dwells in ſilence, and he's the wiſeſt man that keeps
<pb facs="tcp:152166:3"/>
the privacy and recluſeneſs of his own ville.<note place="margin">Appion.</note> 
               <hi>Hannibal</hi> once told <hi>Scipio,</hi> that it had been better both for <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Carthage,</hi> if both of them had been contented with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their own bounds; and poſſibly it had been more honourable both for our brethren of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and our ſelves, had we made our liſts more private, and plaid our prizes onely behind the Curtains, for ſo we had confined and determined our ignorance to our own ſphear, and our defects had been viſible to no eyes but our own.<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> But as <hi>Antalcidas</hi> objected to <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilans,</hi> The <hi>Spartans</hi> have made the <hi>Thebanes</hi> fight whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would or no; the exaſperations and bitterneſs of our brethren,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> have lent cowards courage, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd us to combate whether we would or no; <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt pati nec licere quert;</hi> 'Tis a hard caſe to be hurt, and to have our mouthes ſtopt; to ſuffer, and to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged not to complain; <hi>Qui unam patitur iujuriam invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat aliam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 'Tis a certain rule with the men of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. If you take a blow from them on one cheek, you cannot be Chriſtians in their Calender unleſs you turn the other alſo. We had well hoped, that what <hi>Tully</hi> notes to be the eloquence of <hi>Atticus, Reſpondere ſciat me ſibi dum taceo,</hi> our ſilence and our patience might have been good Orators for us to have anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the pretenſions of their power, the diſguiſes of their popular diſcourſes, and the harſh proceedings towards us but the more we ſuffered, they triumphed the more; and becauſe it was our judgement and choice to dwell in ſilence; they thought we either could not or durſt not ſpeak. But <hi>nemo nobis amicis uti poteſt &amp; Adulatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> They ſhall find we are their friends, but not their Paraſites; we will ſpeak that truth which we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:152166:3"/>
beſeech the good ſpirit to lead them and us into all truth; and in this mean and inconſiderable ſervice, we appeal to the 1000 witneſſes within us, that we ſpeak nothing out of pride or envy, or with unchriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon our ſufferings; but with a hearty deſire of peace, that they or we may be convinc'd, and at laſt meet by a unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not preſent the Rooms and model of the whole houſe in the Porch, yet we ſhall preface a reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of thoſe grievances, which made us open our mouthes in this diſcourſe, <hi>Ne extorqueretur nobis cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Lucii Cottae patrocinio,</hi> leſt we might ſeem to fear the Giant of Presbytery, and to think it were onely that <hi>Palladium</hi> that would preſerve the City of God.</p>
            <p>About 7 months ſince, the Claſſis of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> publiſht their Breviats or cenſures, againſt all that came not in to them for trial and examination, wherein they go to the high waies, and compel all to come in and give ſubmiſſion to their Government, by ſubjecting themſelves to examination by the Miniſters and Elders, not onely ſuch as may be ſuſpected to be ignorant or ſcandalous, but all, of all elevations, of all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, muſt come under the Inquiſition, not ſo much we fear to fit them for the Sacrament, as to teach them obedience, that they may know themſelves,<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> as <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſaid of the Senate, that they are <hi>homines ad ſervitutem nati,</hi> to owe an obedience to their new Maſters, which they muſt pay under the grand penalties of ſuſpenſion and excommunication.</p>
            <p>I anſwer to theſe, <hi>Bruta fulmina,</hi> we with all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and humility ſent them one ſingle ſheet of paper, deſiring ſatisfaction in ſome things wherein our reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:152166:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and religion obliged us to be of a different judgement from them; This one ſheet they return'd in ſeven, an anſwer long enough, if it be ſound enough.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfie us in our ſcruples, and in their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, they pretend for what they do, both an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and civil function, a Commiſſion from Chriſt and the State alſo: But that maxime of the ancient will here be found true <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Our own Lawes built upon paſſion and intereſt, are commonly lawleſſe; It is apparent to us, that their new Lights have no light from Antiquity or primitive forms; that their new Rules have no eſtabliſhment, either by the Lawes of the Chriſtan Church, or the Lawes of this Land. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaid of <hi>Origen,</hi> That <hi>ingenii ſui acumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na putat eccleſia eſſe Sacramenta,</hi> an imagination ſure of our Presbyters, that the <hi>placita</hi> of their own wills muſt paſs for civil and divine conſtitutions. We wonder that men pretending to Learning and Religion, ſhould not onely call in the Lord of truth to abett the phanſies of men, but ſhould alſo pretend to encouragement and Commiſſions from the State to ſecond their prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
            <p>It hath pleaſed his Highneſs in his wiſdome and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, to ſecure all godly and peaceable men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Jeſus Chriſt, from thoſe Ordinances which the rigour of Presbytery had mounted againſt them; but where he gives the leaſt incouragement for this power uſurped by them, we find not; and therefore we think 'tis friendly advice, that they take heed leaſt their unguided zeal or intereſt precipitate them into a premunire, ſince under colour of Authority, they have made Lawes and Canons, and publiſhed them openly in the Church for
<pb facs="tcp:152166:4"/>
all to obey upon pain of excommunication, not onely againſt all the ancient known Lawes of elder date, but alſo contrary to the preſent eſtabliſhment and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie under which we now live.</p>
            <p>'Tis a trouble to us, to hear them cry out againſt Prelacy and Epiſcopacy, as onely an artificial and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical device to Lord it over Gods inheritance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed their little fingers are heavier then the Prelates loins; though they tell us their way is a friendly, meek, and ſocial way, we find it not; they make us onely as Publicans and Heathens; it ſhould ſeem that all that they intended in the change of Church-Government, was onely to ſlice the Dioceſan into Parochiall Biſhops; and with him in <hi>Lucian,</hi> To cut out the old uſeleſs Moons into fine new Stars, every one of which claim the ſame influence and dominion over the people which the Prelates did.</p>
            <p>'Tis a trouble to us, to hear them inveigh againſt Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, againſt the Novatian and Donatiſts of old, when they walk in their ſteps, maintaine their principles, and eſpouſe their quarrels. We are told by the Church Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, That the doctrine againſt mixt-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was a brat begotten by <hi>Novatus,</hi> nurſt up by <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> and <hi>Audius,</hi> but it grew not till <hi>Donatus</hi> became its foſter-Father, then indeed it flouriſht and ſpread amain, till St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> by his judicious and clear oppoſition did baniſh it, that, and the ſubſequent Ages; the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts of the laſt age called it back into <hi>Germany, Quod aruit in ſe refloruit in illis;</hi> they grafted upon the old ſtock, and wanted nothing of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> but to be called ſo. Now amongſt other of their dangerous and
<pb facs="tcp:152166:5"/>
erroneous principles, <hi>Bullinger</hi> notes this for one of the chief, <hi>De doctrinâ, caenae ſcrupuloſe quaerunt Anabaptiſtae, quorum cauſâ caena dominica ſit inſtituta.</hi> They were nice and ſcrupulous, and inquiſitive concerning the Lords Supper, conluding it was only to be given to the Saints, and concluding the Saints to their own folds.</p>
            <p>This is the direct practiſe of the Scottiſh and Engliſh Presbytery; becauſe the Parliament formerly, and now his Highneſs, in their wiſdom and prudence have ſo blunted the edge of their ſecular power, that they cannot hurt us with that, they fly to their religious ſhifts, and what <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Goliah</hi>'s ſword, ſurely they ſay of the holy Sacrament, <hi>There's none like unto that;</hi> no engine ſo likely to teach us obedience, and to give them the ſoveraignty as that. They impale the ſupper of Chriſt to their own incloſures, and as abſolute Judges of all communicants, keep back all perſons that have not their Shiboleth ready, that will not fall down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that Idol which they have ſet up. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were hard Taskmaſters, to expect the children of Iſrael ſhould make Bricks, and make ſtraw too, to require the ſame number of bricks without materials to make them of: this is ſomething like the ſeverity of our new Maſters, they cenſure for not doing that which they render to us impoſſible: If we come not to the Lords Supper, we muſt be excommunicate; and they will not permit us to come, becauſe we are ignorant, or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or prophane; and 'tis proof enough we are ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are too ſtout to fall down and worſhip their imaginations.</p>
            <p>Tis a trouble to us, that men who impropriate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the name of Saints, and would have the world
<pb facs="tcp:152166:5"/>
to think them the onely Chriſtians, ſhould be ſo far from that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that meekneſs and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Goſpel, that they are ſtill of the old legall ſpirit, to eradicate and deſtroy all that are not of their way: Inſtead of ſweetning and indearing the ſpirits of men, that they may come to the knowledge of the truth and be ſaved, they irritate and imbitter them by their two bold judging in private, and by their fierce and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere cenſures in publick, as if indeed it were their work to deliver them up unto Satan.</p>
            <p>Theſe things have forc'd us contrary to our own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and inclinations, to appear in publick, nor on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our own vindication, but in defence of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and civil conſtitutions, well hoping that theſe mean indeavours will encourage ſome worthy and learned Champions to take up Arms for the defence of that cauſe which we love: what we have done, <hi>quale quale ſit,</hi> what ever it be, inaſmuch as in the ſincerity of our hearts we profeſs 'tis done, <hi>ſine ullo studio contentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> without any pleaſure or delight in contention, but onely for the love of truth, we hope our good God will give it a more gracious ſucceſs, and good men will give it a more charitable reception.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:152166:6"/>
            <head>Errata ſic Corrigenda.</head>
            <p>PAge 81. line 25. for whereas, read whereat. p. 82 l. 2 theſe, r. thoſe. p. 83 l. 10 Anſwer as it is to, r. Anſwer it is to be. ibid. l. 16 pray, r. pay. p. 84 l. 32 See, r. So. p. 85 l. unaninous, r. unanimous. p. 87 l. 24 referring, r. reſtoring. p. 88 l. 13. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, r. excommunication. Ih the Preface, p. 3. l. 30. for I, r. In.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152166:6"/>
            <head>At the firſt Claſſe at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> Septem. <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1657.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN purſuance of an Order of the laſt Provincial, the firſt Claſſe doth humbly repreſent to this Aſſembly their apprehenſions in the caſe to them propounded in a draught prepared for the ſeveral Congregations belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to their own Aſſociation, if it ſhall be approved of by this Aſſembly, and which they do wholely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their Judgments.</p>
            <p>It being repreſented to this Claſſe, and much complained of, and offence being taken, That in the ſeveral Congregations, (if not all) belonging to the Aſſociation, there are many perſons of all ſorts, that are members of Congregations, and publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoy ſeveral priviledges; as, the hearing of the Word, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church, and baptizing of their children; and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for injuries done unto them, That yet live in a total and ſinfull neglect of the Lords Supper, that are ſcandalous and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive in their lives, drunkards, unclean perſons, ſwearers, Sabbath-breakers, neglecters of Family-duties, that will not ſubject themſelves to the preſent government of the Church, but live as lawleſs perſons, out of their rank and order, and there are ſundry that are groſly ignorant in the main points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Theſe are to give notice, that this Claſſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152166:7"/>
theſe things to heart, and much grieved for them, do pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and make known;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That every Miniſter belonging to this Aſſociation, ſhall ſet apart one or two dayes, or more of the week dayes, in every moneth, for the catechizing of the ſeveral families belonging to their reſpective Congregations; and for the information of the ignorant in thoſe families, and that the families to be catechized on each of ſuch dayes, ſet apart for that purpoſe, have notice the Lords day before, to meet the Miniſters either at the Church or Chappel, or the Miniſters houſe, or ſome other houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Congregation, that may be convenient for the neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing families to meet at, that ſhall be appointed for ſuch a day, as may be judged meeteſt by the ſeveral Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That notice ſhall be taken of all perſons that forſake the publick Aſſemblies of the Saints, and conſtantly turn their backs of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That like notice ſhall be taken of all ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That they ſhall be privately admoniſhed, according to the order preſcribed by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. once or twice, to ſee if they will reform; and that the Miniſter, when hee catechizeth the ſeveral families, ſhall exhort ſuch perſons in them as hee findes to be of a competent knowledg, and are blameleſſe in life, that they preſent themſelves to the Elderſhip, that they may be admitted to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That if they will neither hearken to private admonition, nor admonition of the Elderſhip, their names ſhall be publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed openly in the ſeveral Congregations, and they warned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all to reform.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That if after all this they ſhall continue obſtinate, they ſhall be caſt out, and excommunicated.</p>
            <p>Theſe things this Claſſe thought fit to give publick notice of, being very ſenſible, that, for the want of the vigorous exerciſe of Church diſcipline, ignorance, Atheiſm, and licentiouſneſſe grows upon us, to the great diſhonor of God, ſcandal of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the hazzard and undoing of many pretious ſouls, and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152166:7"/>
laying a blot on ſeveral Congregations; and therefore they are reſolved, (ſeeing themſelves neceſſitated, to this ſeverity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, for the freeing themſelves from the great guilt of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of their own duty, that otherwiſe they ſhall be under) to make uſe of that power that Chriſt hath committed to them, for edification, and not for deſtruction; although it would be their farr greater joy, that there might not be occaſion of uſing ſharpneſſe: and therefore they do earneſtly in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt beſeech all thoſe that are ignorant, that they would apply themſelves diligently to the uſe of all publick and private means for their information, ſubmitting themſelves with all readineſſe to be inſtructed; and to conſider, that without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the minde cannot be good: and they do alſo in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, exhort and warn all ſuch as live ſcandalouſly, and in the practice of open ſins, that they break off their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities by repentance, and turn unto God ſpeedily with their whole heart, that they neither incurr the cenſure of being caſt out of the Church here, nor by continuing in their ſinfull courſe, be kept for ever entering into the kingdome of Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>And touching ſuch as turn their backs of the Lords Supper conſtantly, this Claſſe doth wiſh them ſeriouſly, to conſider what an account they will be able to give unto Jeſus Chriſt, for their living in the dayly neglect of an ordinance that is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding neceſſary for their own comfort and growth in grace; and that they would lay aſide all prejudice, whatever it is that hinders, and ſubmit themſelves unto wholeſom doctrine, for their own good, as this Claſſe hath been ready on their part to expreſſe all tenderneſſe toward the weak, and a willingneſſe to condeſcend to the meaneſt, for the removing all occaſions of ſtumbling, ſo farr as lies in their power. And yet, conſidering the fearfull danger that all ſuch do lay themſelves open unto, that ſhall eat and drink the Body and Blood of the Lord unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, they do warn whoſoever comes to the Lords Table, to take ſpecial care ſo often as they come, to examine themſelves, leſt they eat and drink their own damnation.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the exerciſe of Church diſcipline muſt begin at private perſons, and that if they neglect their duty of watching
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152166:8"/>
over, and admoniſhing one another, and bringing complaints to the Elderſhip as there is occaſion, little or nothing can be done for the thorow reformation of the ſeveral Congregations; this Claſſe doth therefore warn all and every of the members be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto them, to conſider the great guilt they will lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if they through their neglect, obſtruct ſo needfull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a work, and doth expect therefore in all faithfulneſſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide all partiality, ſlaviſhneſſe, and ſelf-reſpects, they ſhould addreſſe themſelves to the diſcharge of their duties, that if any walk diſorderly, and will not be reclaimed by private admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they making complaint thereof to the Elderſhip, courſe may be taken for excommunicating of the obſtinate, and thereby purging out the old leven, to the glory of God, the delivering their own ſouls from that guilt they will otherwiſe lye under, the preſerving the Ordinances from prophanation, and the reſt of the lump from being levened, the ſtopping of the mouthes of ſuch as ſeek occaſion againſt us, and finally the everlaſting welfare and ſalvation of the ſouls of thoſe that go aſtray.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>By the Provincial Aſſembly at</hi> Preſton,
<date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>RICHARD HEYRICKE Moderator <hi>pro tempore.</hi>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This Preſentation is approved by the Provincial Aſſembly,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>THOMAS JOHNSON, Moderator.</item>
                     <item>EDWARD GEE, Scribe.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152166:8"/>
            <head>To the Elderſhip of the ſeverall congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations belonging to the Aſſociation of the Firſt Claſſe at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Province of <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> Theſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Give us leave to ſalute you, in your own Terms.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE have ſeen and ſeriouſly weighed that paper draught, Intituled <hi>A preſentation of the firſt Claſſe at</hi> Mancheſter, <hi>dated the</hi> 8. <hi>of Sept.</hi> 1657. confirmed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Aſſembly at <hi>Preſton, Octob.</hi> 6. and publiſhed at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> Church the 22. of <hi>Nov.</hi> in the aforeſaid year: and do publiſh this our ſenſe, and Apprehenſion of it, as far as is plain to us, not reſting in the Judgement and determination of any General Council contrary thereunto (if any ſuch ſhould be) much leſs to one of your Provincial Aſſemblies; Though you ſeem to ſubmit to your Provincial, what you will hardly grant to a General Council: In which we diſſent from you; Though in other things we ſhall joyn, as firſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We joyn with you, in a deep ſenſe of the ſeverall groſs ſins and errours of the times, deſiring earneſtly to mourn, firſt for our own, next for the ſins of others of our Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and fellow members of that Church, whereof Chriſt is the Head: We are grieved together with you, for the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and offenſive lives of ſuch as live in drunkeneſs, unclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſwearing, prophanation of the Sabbath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We are alſo ſenſible with you, that there are ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, groſſely ignorant, in the main points of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You with us again (we hope) are ſenſible and grieved (though you do not at all mention them) for the groſs errours
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152166:9"/>
in judgement, and the damnable Doctrine of many, who have rent themſelves into as many ſeverall hereſies, as they have into Sects and Schiſmes.</p>
            <p>Thus far we agree, nay more, touching the way of informing the ignorant, and reforming the wicked and erroneous, we ſhall not much diſſent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>And firſt for the information and inſtruction of the ignorant, by way of Catechizing, before they be admitted to the Sacrament;</hi> The courſe by you publiſhed (provided it be in publique) little differeth from the order preſcribed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other reformed Churches abroad, before any be admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For thoſe who erre ſo groſſely, whether in Doctrinals, or points of diſcipline, thereby renting from a true conſtituted Church:</hi> Though you ſpeak nothing either of their ſin or puniſhment, yet we hope, you with us do hold, That the Churches lawfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, have the power of the Keys committed to them, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate ſuch offenders.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For ſuch as are ſcandalous and wicked in their lives;</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, private and publique, is to be obſerved according to Chriſts rule <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. but if they ſtill continue, and will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, the Churches lawfull Paſtors have power to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſuch.</p>
            <p>Thus far we accord in judgement, touching the way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ignorant, and reforming wicked perſons, and ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical; which courſe is ſo fully warranted by the Word of God, and the conſtant practiſe of the Catholique Church, that we are not ſo wavering and unſetled in our apprehenſions of the caſe, as to ſubmit either it or them, either wholly or in part, to the contrary judgement and determination of a General Council of the Eaſtern or Weſtern Churches; much leſs, to a new termed Provincial Aſſembly at <hi>Preſton,</hi> wherein we no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle differ from you.</p>
            <p>Other parts of your Paper are full of darkneſs, to which we cannot ſo fully aſſent, till further explicated and unfolded by you. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas you ſay, <hi>That in the ſeveral congregations (if not in all) belonging to this Aſſociation, there are many perſons of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152166:9"/>
all ſorts that are members of congregations,</hi> &amp;c. you ſeem to hint, that though your grief may be general (as ours) for all offenders, yet your cenſures extend onely to thoſe who have admitted themſelves members of ſome Congregation within your Aſſociation, and yet live inordinately, and will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed: If ſo, then we who never were any members or aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates of yours, are not within the verge and compaſs of your Presbyterian diſcipline; for what have you to do to judge thoſe that are without?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But whereas your complaint, and offence taken, is, <hi>That many there are of all ſorts, who will not ſubmit themſelves to the preſent Government of the Church, but live like lawleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons out of their rank and order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If by the preſent Government of the Church, you mean your own (as may ſtrongly be conjectured you do) then are we alſo comprehended therein, and muſt fall within your cenſure, and not onely we, but all Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, and all other, of what Profeſſion, and Religion ſoever, who live within the Pariſh, muſt be taken for members of ſome one Congregation within your Aſſociation, and ſo driven into the common fold of Presbytery, and be ſubject to your Government: And this (as we ſuppoſe) is the cheif deſign of you, in this, as in other tranſactions of yours, to ſubject all to your Government, which you garniſh over with the ſpecious title, of <hi>Chriſts Government, Throne,</hi> and <hi>Scepter.</hi> Presbytery is the main thing driven at here; and however ſhe cometh uſhered in with a Godly pretence of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for the ſins and ignorance of the times, and a duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon you, to exerciſe the power which Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you, for edification, and not for deſtruction; yet theſe are but as ſo many waſte papers wherein Presbyterie is wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, to make it look more handſomely, and paſs more currently; but beware we muſt, for <hi>latet anguis in Herbâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But you ſay, <hi>For want of the vigorous exerciſe of this Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, ignorance, Atheiſm, and Licentiouſneſs grows upon us, and men live as lawleſſe perſons, out of their rank and order, becauſe not ſubject to your preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> We pray for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152166:10"/>
throughout his Highneſs Dominions, as is conſonant to the will of God, and Univerſall practice of primitive Churches, that Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline may be exerciſed, in the hands of them, to whom it was committed by Chriſt, and left by him, to be transferred from hand to hand to the end of the World; and ſhall readily joyn with you in humble addreſſes, to his Highneſs, and his great Council, for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch a Church Government.</p>
            <p>In the mean time though there may be ſuch, who (as you ſay) live as lawleſs perſons, out of their rank and order, yet are they ſubject to law, and therefore ſubject to puniſhment, for though your Eccleſiaſtical ſword cannot take hold on them, the civill ſword doth reach them.</p>
            <p>Your Claſs may do well then not to contemn (as in charity we hope you do not) the authority of the civill Magiſtrate, but in ſtead of warning all and every member belonging to them, to complain to the Elderſhip, of thoſe that walk diſorderly, and will not be reclaimed, to the end they may excommunicate them, That they exhort them to complain to the civill Magiſtrate, whoſe ſword of Juſtice is ſharper and longer, and likely to work a greater reformation in the lives, and manners of men, by a corporal and pecuniary Mulct, then any ſword of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or other Church cenſure your Elderſhip can any way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto;</p>
            <p>There are other parts of your paper do remain likewiſe dark, which we deſire may be made plain unto us; for whereas you ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are many perſons of all ſorts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to the preſent Government of the Church, but live as lawleſs perſons, out of their rank and order:</hi> Our Quaeres thereupon are;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why Government <hi>in ſingulari?</hi> is there no Eccleſiaſticall Government but yours? may not another Church have its Government different from yours, yet not different from that which Chriſt hath preſcribed in his Word? <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, yea; <hi>Scimus enim unicuique Eccleſiae, &amp;c.</hi> And accordingly there are other Churches in <hi>England</hi> different in Government from yours, and as good as yours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152166:10"/>But if you ſay yours is the Government, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) by way of eminency, as Chriſts own Government more immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and <hi>jure divino,</hi> which you ſo much defend, then why (the preſent) is there no preſent Government in any Church or Aſſembly of Saints, but where your diſcipline is erected? Are all the reſt at preſent without Government? or where hath yours been this 1500. years paſt till this preſent? Hath <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm</hi> ſo overſpread the face of the Church that Chriſts own Government could never get footing till this preſent? But now ſubjection is required thereto of all, yet many of all ſorts will not ſubject, but live as lawleſs perſons, out of their rank and order.</p>
            <p>Our next Quaere is;</p>
            <p>What? muſt all thoſe that obſerve not your ranks and orders, ſubject not themſelves to your preſent Government, be taken for lawleſs perſons, out of their rank and order? Yea; for ſo this cloſe connexion of yours ſeems to import, <hi>(viz.) many who do not ſubject but live,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In your paper you further proceed, and make it an order, <hi>That notice ſhall be taken of all perſons, that forſake the publick aſſembly of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We would gladly know how far you extend this Saintſhip, this Church and aſſembly of Saints, if to your own Church one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuch as ſubject themſelves to your Government; then S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Anſwer againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who would not acknowledg a Church in the World but amongſt themſelves, may alſo be yours, <hi>O Impudentem Vocem!</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Illa non eſt, Quia tu in illa non es: Vide nè tu ideo non ſis, nam illa erit etſi tu non ſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if your charity reach further, then to your own aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, then you make lawleſs perſons, ſuch as will not ſubject themſelves to your Government, Saints, and members at leaſt of the inviſible Triumphant Church, though none of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent viſible militant Church; and then your charity over reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>Again, we are unſatisfied in the Word <hi>(Publique) the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aſſemblies of the Saints,</hi> What? do not private aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152166:11"/>
pleaſe you? We preſume you are not againſt private meetings, your own practice ſpeaks the contrary? But you will binde all (notwithſtanding your private Aſſemblies) to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent your publique alſo, other wayes they ſhall be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of: What? though they cannot ſubmit to your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Leave you no room for tender conſciences? The Laws of the Land have otherwayes provided: And if you, under color of authority, will make Laws and Edicts, and publiſh them openly in the Church, for all to obey, upon pain of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, contrary to the Laws in force, whether you do it in contempt of the civill power, or through ignorance of the Laws; which later is rather to be ſuppoſed, in a charitable and favourable conſtruction, yet in what ſenſe ſoever it be taken, we much queſtion, and it concerns you to look to it, whether you have not run your ſelves into a <hi>praemunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, whereas you ſay, <hi>That like notice ſhall be taken of all ſcandalous perſons.</hi> Our next Quaere is; Whether thoſe that forſake the publique Aſſemblies of Saints in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> order, may not be taken for ſcandalous, and ſo comprehended in this 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. If ſo, <hi>Quare oneramini ritibus?</hi> why do you lengthen out your paper, and burden us with traditions, in multiplying of orders <hi>ſine neceſſitate ad Arthritim uſque?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> orders againſt thoſe that forſake the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Aſſemblies of Saints, and ſuch as are ſcandalous, comes in a fourth, touching the <hi>Catechumeniſts</hi> in the firſt order men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; <hi>(viz.) That the Miniſter when he Catechizeth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Families, ſhall exhort ſuch perſons in them as he findes, be of competent knowledge, and are blameleſs in life, that they preſent themſelves to the Elderſhip, that they may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Sacrament of the Lord ſupper:</hi> But what if they will not preſent themſelves before the Elderſhip? <hi>The Miniſter muſt exhort and admoniſh them.</hi> What if ſtill they refuſe? <hi>Their names ſhall be publiſhed openly in the ſeveral congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and they warned before all to reform.</hi> That's the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. order. Mark! Men of blameleſs life and knowledge muſt be warned before all to reform.</p>
            <p>But what if after all this they will not reform, but continue obſtinate? <hi>Then no admiſſion to the Sacrament;</hi> that's implyed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152166:11"/>
in the fourth order; There's their <hi>Excommunicatio minor:</hi> But that's not all, a higher cenſure yet; <hi>They ſhall be caſt out, and excommunicated;</hi> So ſaith the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and laſt order, the great Excommunication, which caſteth out of the Church alſo, and judgeth them no better, then Heathens, and Publicans, notwithſtanding all their piety and knowledge.</p>
            <p>So that, in brief, all wilfully ignorant and Scandalous are to be excommunicated; and not onely they, but the knowing, and blameleſs of life, if they preſent not themſelves to the Elderſhip. Theſe things premiſed, lying ſadly on our ſpirits and conſciences, as not ſound and orthodox, for which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo readily joyn with you, till further ſatisfaction be given us, and which the publiſher of your Paper promiſed ſhould be given to all that did deſire, We therefore thought fit to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie theſe our ſcruples to you, and ſhall wait earneſtly for a ſpeedy ſatisfaction in the particulars, remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Brethren <hi>deſirous of Truth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace in the Church.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Iſaac Allen.</item>
                     <item>Jo: Pollett.</item>
                     <item>Tho: Preſtwich.</item>
                     <item>Leonard Egerton.</item>
                     <item>Ferdinando Stanley.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152166:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>At</hi> Mancheſter, <hi>Feb. 23. 1657.</hi> The Anſwer of the Firſt Claſsis within the Province of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> unto a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per preſented unto them at their Claſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal meeting, <hi>Jan. 12. 1657.</hi> by certain Gentlemen, ſubſcribed by them and ſundry others within the bounds of this Aſſociation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WEE have peruſed your Paper, and do finde in it ſundry miſtakes, and ſome manifeſt wreſtings of our plain meaning, in that Paper of ours, which was publiſhed in our ſeveral Congregations: And wee are alſo ſenſible of the ſharp reflections in it, upon the Government, that is committed to our mannage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and on our ſelves. But wee ſhall not go about to anſwer you in that kinde: and therefore laying aſide animoſities, and putting away gall and bitterneſſe, in the ſpirit of love and meekneſſe, however in faithfulneſſe and plainneſſe, wee ſhall endeavor to ſhew you your Errors and rectifie your miſtakes. And wee do thus farr acknowledg your fair dealing, (for which wee give you hearty thanks) that you addreſſe your ſelves unto us, giving us thereby the opportunity, both to vindicate our ſelves, and give you a right underſtanding of the maters where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Our leaſure will not permit us to ſpend time about imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152166:12"/>
but yet, that you may not conceive wee are deſtitute of Civil Authority, (which you in your Paper minde us not to contemn, and wee our ſelves do profeſſedly teſtifie all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects unto, as in duty wee are bound) wee intreat you to take notice, That the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament having reſolved to eſtabliſh the Presbyterian Government throughout the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> did <hi>Auguſt</hi> 19. 1645. publiſh their directions, after advice had with the Aſſembly of Divines, for the electing and chuſing of ruling Elders in all the Congregations, and in the Claſſical Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies for the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Counties of the Kingdom, for the ſpeedy ſettling of the Presbyterian Government. In theſe directions, (as may be ſeen <hi>pag.</hi> 8.) they did ordain, <hi>That in the ſeveral Counties cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſons, Miniſters and others, ſhould be appointed by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Parliament, who ſhould conſider, how the ſeveral Counties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively might be moſt conveniently divided into diſtinct Claſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Presbyteries; and what Miniſters and others were fit to be of each Claſſis. And that they ſhould accordingly make ſuch divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and nomination of perſons for each Claſſical Presbytery. Which diviſions, and perſons ſo named for every diviſion, the appointed ſhould be certified up to the Parliament.</hi> And they further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, <hi>That the ſaid ſeveral Claſſes reſpectively being appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Parliament, within their ſeveral precincts ſhould have power to conſtitute Congregational Elderſhips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to theſe directions, the perſons by them appointed for this County met, and did conſider, how it might be moſt conveniently divided into diſtinct Claſſical Presbyteries, and what Miniſters and others were fit to be of each Claſſis: and alſo made ſuch a diviſion and nomination accordingly, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the ſame up to the Parliament; All which being done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their directions and appointment, It was reſolved by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, <hi>Oct.</hi> 2. 1646. <hi>That they did approve of the diviſion of the County of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>into nine Claſſical Presbyteries repreſented from the ſaid County.</hi> And it was further reſolved, <hi>That the ſaid Houſes did approve of the Miniſters and other perſons repreſented from the County of</hi> Lancaſter, <hi>as fit to be of the ſeveral and reſpective Claſſes, into
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152166:13"/>
which the ſaid County was divided.</hi> Which diviſion of this County into nine Claſſical Presbyteries, and the approval there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the ſaid Lords and Commons was forthwith printed and publiſhed. In this diviſion ſo made and approved, <hi>The firſt Claſſis is to contain</hi> Mancheſter <hi>Pariſh,</hi> Preſtwich <hi>Pariſh,</hi> Oldham <hi>Pariſh,</hi> Flixton <hi>Pariſh,</hi> Eccles <hi>Pariſh, and</hi> Aſhton <hi>under-line Pariſh,</hi> as by what was then printed, and is yet extant, is to be ſeen. Further, wee wiſh you to take notice, That in your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Directions <hi>pag.</hi> 3. <hi>Direction</hi> 6. it is there thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, <hi>That all Pariſhes and places whatſoever (as well privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged places and exempt Juriſdictions, as others) be brought under the government of Congregational, Claſſical, and National Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. Provided, that the Chappels or places in the houſes of the Peers of this Realm ſhould continue free for the exerciſe of Divine Duties, to be performed according to the Directory.</hi> And alſo, that it was ordered by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 21. 1646. <hi>That the ſeveral Claſſes in</hi> Lancaſhire <hi>ſhould be one Province;</hi> As appears by their Order to that purpoſe. As there is alſo another Order of theirs of <hi>Octob.</hi> 16. 1648. enabling the ſeveral Claſſes within this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to ſend their Delegates to meet in a Provincial Aſſembly in <hi>Preſton,</hi> and appointing the time of their firſt meeting; the number of the Delegates, that were to be ſent to the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; and the <hi>Quorum</hi> of the Aſſembly, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that had been made before by the Parliament, before any Provincial Aſſembly could by virtue of their Authority be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to act Provincially. By which account thus given it is manifeſt, That the ſetting up the Presbyterian Government in this County: The diviſion of it into ſeveral Claſſes: The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe Claſſes into a Province, and their Acting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincially: As alſo the appointing this Claſſis to be the firſt, (that is, the firſt in regard of the number onely, the account beginning here) was all done by Authority of Parliament. And that, when wee call our ſelves the firſt Claſſis within the Province of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> wee are awarranted thereto by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Parliament. And ſo your <hi>Saluting us in our own terms,</hi> (which wee gave not to our ſelves, till the Parliament had firſt given them to us) will not ſeem ſtrange to them, that then did,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152166:13"/>
or now do, acknowledg that Authority and Power, which the Parliament exerciſed in thoſe times. Eſpecially conſidering there was nothing done ſince, either by that Parliament or any other, or by his Highneſſe and the laſt Parliament, that takes from us what was then granted, and as wee ſhall clear further anon.</p>
            <p>In your Preface to what in your Paper you have to ſay unto us, there is in the firſt place a miſtake of that title, which was given by us unto ours; (which you call a Paper draught) for it was not by us intituled a Preſentation (as you call it) but a <hi>Draught, that repreſented to the Provincial Aſſembly our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions in a caſe by them propounded unto us;</hi> And was approved by the Provincial, under the Title of a <hi>Repreſentation.</hi> But this perhaps was but the miſtake of the Scribe, and wee inſiſt not on it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is of greater weight and moment, to take notice of what you publiſh as your ſenſe and apprehenſions of it, (not reſting in the judgment or determination of any general Council contrary thereunto) if any ſuch ſhould be, much leſſe to one of our Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Aſſemblies. Although you tell us, wee ſeem to ſubmit to our Provincial, what wee will hardly grant to a general Council; in which you profeſſe to differ from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee know very well, and have learned better from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, then to reſolve our Faith into the determination of any company of men on Earth whatſoever, or to build our Faith on the Judgment of Synods, Provincial or National; or of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils, that have been heretofore, or that may be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Wee are ſure all men are fallible; and Faith, that is a ſure and certain grace, muſt have a ſure and certain Foundation, which is onely the infallible and written Word of God. And if this onely be your meaning, you have not us differing from you. But yet when wee conſider, That Synods and Councils, rightly conſtituted and regularly called, as they may be then of great uſe for light and guidance, ſo alſo that they are the Ordinance of God, and by him inveſted with authority, and ſo have an autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative Judgment belonging to them, and which is not in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, wee dare not contemn them, nor ſpeak ſleightly of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152166:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152166:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152166:15"/>
them. And ſeeing the higher Aſſemblies have greater Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then the lower, (as there is more power in the whole, then in the part; in the whole body, then in any one, or ſome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) and that, however wee are well enough ſatisfied, that wee have the Authority of a Claſſe, yet wee are under the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Provincial Aſſembly; Wee ſee not wherein wee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, that wee ſubmitted our apprehenſions, in the Caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by that Aſſembly unto us, unto their Judgment. There is concerning matters of Religion <hi>Judicium Privatum,</hi> or <hi>a Private Judgment;</hi> and this belongs to all Chriſtians, who are to fee with their own eyes, and judge, concerning what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for them to know and believe in matters of this nature. This Judgment, as there is good reaſon why wee ſhould allow it to our ſelves, ſo wee ſhould Lord it over mens conſciences, if wee ſhould deny it to any. There is alſo <hi>Judicium Publicum &amp; Authoritativum, A Publick and an Authoritative Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and this is either Concional, which belongs to every lawfull Miniſter (to whom the Key of Doctrine is committed) by himſelf ſingly: or elſe it is Juridical, and this belongs to Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Councils, who having the Key of Diſcipline, are inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with authority to inquire into, try, examine, cenſure and judg of matters of Doctrine and Diſcipline authoritatively, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be tyed to the rule of Gods Word in ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as Judges to the Law) &amp; likewiſe to cenſure offenders ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their merit, when ſuch caſes are regularly and orderly brought before them. And in this ſenſe it was, that we ſubmitted our apprehenſions in the Paper publiſhed to the Judgment of the Provincial Aſſembly. And we believe, when the Apoſtle tells us, 1. Cor. 14.32. <hi>That the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets:</hi> And our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, Mat. 18. <hi>Tell the Church.</hi> And when wee conſider, what was practiſed by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and certain others (who, upon occaſion of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that aroſe in the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> about a matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, were ſent up from that Church to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders about that queſtion) from theſe and other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptural grounds wee had ſufficient ground for ſo doing. Wee are ſure alſo, That <hi>Whitaker de Conciliis queſtione quintâ,</hi> and <hi>Chamierus</hi> in his <hi>Panſtratiâ de oecumenico. Pontifice, ubi de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152166:15"/>
Papae in Eccleſiâ, cap.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 14. And generally all our Proteſtant Divines againſt the Papiſts, alledging the Texts above-mentioned and others, do prove abundantly, that in the ſenſe declared, the Pope is to be ſubject to a general Council, wherein alſo ſundry Papiſts do concurr with them. And queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs, if in the time of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (who was no contemner of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods &amp; Councils) any in this ſenſe had declared, that they would not have ſubmitted their apprehenſions to their judgment, hee would have cried out againſt them as well as againſt the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, <hi>O impudentem vocem!</hi> And we hope, when you have weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the matter better, you will not in this ſenſe ſee any reaſon to refuſe to ſubmit either your ſenſe and apprehenſions of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or what you may publiſh as your own private Judgments in other matters about Religion, to the Judgment of a general Council, ſuppoſing it might be had.</p>
            <p>Wee have now done with your Preface, and come to the matter it ſelf, wherein you profeſſe,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>To joyn with us in a deep ſenſe of the ſeveral groſſe ſins and errors of the times, deſiring earneſtly to mourn firſt for your own ſins, next for the ſins of others, &amp;c.</hi> And here wee do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pray, that neither wee nor you may any of us condemn our ſelves, either by profeſſing our ſorrow, for what ſins we may practiſe, or by refuſing to help forward the good that we profeſſe to allow of, but may teſtifie the truth of our ſorrow for our own and other mens ſins, by ſuitable endeavors to reform what is amiſſe in our ſelves, and helping forward every one in his place the reformation of others.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) In the next place, you ſay, <hi>You are alſo ſenſible with us, that there are ſundry perſons groſly ignorant in the main points of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> And if ſo, wee hope you will acknowledg, that where, after the injoying of plenty of Preaching and the publick Catechizing, that hath been uſed for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (and much more where there hath been leſſe of this means) many continue groſly ignorant in the main points of Religion, it is at leaſt not to be condemned in ſuch Miniſters, as ſhall be willing to take the pains by private Catechizing to inſtruct ſuch perſons: This courſe being to the Miniſters a matter of pains
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152166:16"/>
onely; and that hereupon, where the publick Catechizing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not its deſired end, the private may be good and uſefull, that ſo poor ſouls periſh not for lack of knowledg.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Laſtly <hi>You hope, That wee with you are ſenſible and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, though,</hi> you ſay, <hi>wee do not mention them, for the groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in judgment and damnable Doctrine of many, who have rent themſelves into as many ſeveral Hereſies, as they have into Sects and Schiſms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may perceive by the title of our Paper, that it was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of our apprehenſions to the Provincial Aſſembly, in the Caſe to us propounded by the ſaid Provincial, and what that was, wee ſhall particularly declare anon, (although by what wee ſay had been complained of, and repreſented unto us, it might be gathered) and therefore wee were chiefly to apply our ſelves to that, which was therein our main work and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. That the groſſe and damnable errors, that the looſneſſe of theſe times have brought forth, are to be bewailed (if it were poſſible) with tears of blood, is moſt freely to be confeſſed. And whether wee lay them not to heart in ſome poor meaſure, God the ſearcher of all hearts hee knows; as what complaints have been made of theſe by the members of this Claſſis, both in their prayers and preaching, men can witneſſe; and likewiſe what teſtimonies have been given to the truth of Jeſus Chriſt, and againſt the errors of the times, ſubſcribed with their hands and publiſhed to the world, though therein but concurring with the reſt of their Reverend Brethren in this Province, in the Province of <hi>London,</hi> and other Counties of the Land, poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may reade, when wee are in our graves. But as to the moſt of the Congregations belonging to this Claſſis, the great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be looked after was the uſe of our beſt indeavors, for the informing of the ignorant, and the reforming of the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, the numbers of theſe being great, and of thoſe that are ſo groſly erroneous as to maintain damnable doctrines, and whereof you profeſſe your ſelves to be ſo ſenſible, very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, in compariſon of the former: and in ſundry of our Congregations, if not in moſt, (bleſſed be God for it) not any at all, that wee know of. And therefore there was not that reaſon to make any ſuch expreſſe mention of theſe as of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152166:16"/>
former, although in our Paper wee were not herein neither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſilent, as will after appear.</p>
            <p>Having profeſſed your agreement with us thus farr, yo go on to declare your ſelves, <hi>That, touching the way of informing the ignorant, and reforming the wicked and erroneous, you ſhall not much diſſent.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) You ſay, <hi>For the Information and inſtruction of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant by way of Catechizing before they be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the courſe by us publiſhed (provided,</hi> you ſay, <hi>it be in publick) little differeth from the Order preſcribed by the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and other Reformed Churches abroad, before any be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Children and others, (ſo many as it is fit to inſtruct after that manner) be publickly catechized, is that, which we hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh had been &amp; were more generally practiſed in our own Church at home, as it is practiſed by the Reformed Churches abroad. And certainly, had the publick catechizing of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and others been more generally and conſtantly practiſed, there had not been that cauſe to complain of the groſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſundry perſons of ripe years, and ſome of them gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Families, as now there is. Wee do alſo underſtand you by what you do here expreſſe, that you judg it not meet, that the groſly ignorant ſhould be admitted to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in that you ſeem to approve of the practice of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches abroad, (as of our own at home) in taking courſe to inform the ignorant, before they admit them to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; And therefore wee ſee not how you can in reaſon deny, but there ought to be an examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and trial of all perſons, before they be admitted to the Lords Supper, that ſo the groſly ignorant may not be admitted, as they might be, if all promiſcuouſly were admitted without any trial at all.</p>
            <p>But whereas, in this conceſſion about catechizing, you have a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that it be in publick, wee do not ſee, why you ſhould ſo limit it, if it be confeſſed, that it is neceſſary, that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſhould be informed, and that catechizing is an uſefull means to attain that end. You know how it would daſh ſundry know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons to be catechized publickly in the Congregation.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152166:17"/>
But as for thoſe that are conſcious to themſelves, that they are very ignorant, if theſe ſhould be called forth to publique Catechizing, it were more likely to drive them from the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Aſſembly, and ſo from the uſe of all means for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, then be availeable to this end. As touching what was propounded by us in our paper, as the way for their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (though it was not intended for any ſuch a purpoſe as to exclude publique Catechizing) it was done in way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion to the weakeſt, and to ſhew our willingneſs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to any courſe, ſo we might be inſtrumentall to bring poor dark and blinde Souls to the knowledge of Chriſt, and which in our Judgement is more likely to be attained in many, as the caſe ſtands with them, in a more private way of Catechizing in any of the wayes propounded by us, then if we ſhould Catechize all the ſeverall Families publiquely before the whole congregation.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Touching thoſe <hi>that erre ſo groſſely, whether in Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals or points of diſcipline, thereby renting from a true conſtituted Church,</hi> you ſay, <hi>we ſpeak nothing, either of their ſin or puniſhment, yet you hope, we with you do hold, that the Churches lawfull Paſtors have the power of the keyes committed to them, to excommunicate ſuch offenders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have given you the reaſon already, why we made not ſuch expreſs mention of theſe offenders, as of the former, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as you will hereafter perceive) we are not wholly ſilent touching eirher the ſin or puniſhment of theſe. Onely at preſent, becauſe you profeſs to allow of that previous courſe of admonition preſcribed by Chriſt, in reference to the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. before they be excommunicated, but here ſay nothing of any ſuch courſe to be taken with the hereticall or ſchiſmaticall; (though we hope alſo of you, that you diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it not) we ſhall briefly declare, what courſe is to be held by the rules of the Presbyterian Government, before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication paſs againſt theſe offenders, and whereof our paper was not ſilent. This Government, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it gives no toleration to <hi>any ſuch errours, as ſubvert the faith; or any other errours, which overthrow the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if the party, who holds them, ſpreads them, ſeeking to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152166:17"/>
draw others after him, or to any ſuch practiſes, as in their own nature manifeſtly ſubvert that order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace, which Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in his Church.</hi> Theſe being offences cenſured by this Government, (and of which further after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,) yet this Government preſcribes the exerciſe of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long ſuffering (even toward thoſe that do groſſely erre in Doctrine as well as toward thoſe that are ſcandalous in life) in the uſe of all means for the convincing them of their errours; by reaſoning with them out of the Scriptures: as we ſee was practiſed in the Synod, that was held at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and as we ſee the Fathers of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, did not diſdain to reaſon and diſpute with <hi>Arrius</hi> (though he denyed the Deity of Chriſt) before they condemned him: And as alſo other Fathers did with other Hereticks in the Synods, although of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes in vain. That ſo none might have any juſt cauſe to complain, that they were condemned, before they were fully heard. And as touching ſuch as run into ſuch practices, as in their own nature tend manifeſtly to the ſubverting of that order and unity which Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in the Church, it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours with theſe alſo in the uſe of all gentle means to reclaim them, and bring them back again to the Church they have rent themſelves from, before it proceed to cenſure. As it doth alſo put a difference between the ſeducers, and ring-leaders of a Sect, and thoſe that are miſled. Having reſpect not only to the nature of the offence, but alſo to the quality of the offender; and exerciſeth patience and forbearance towards all, ſo long as there is any hope of reducing them by milde correction: Being ever more deſireous to heal, then cut off any member. And thus having declared our ſelves in this, we go an with you.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) For you ſay; <hi>For ſuch as are ſcandalous and wicked in their lives, admonition private and publique is to be obſerved, according to Chriſts rule</hi> Mat. 18. <hi>But if they ſtill continue, and will not reform, the Churches lawfull Paſtors have power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this you fully come up to what we hold, as to the means, that is to be uſed for the reformation of theſe, and we are glad there is an agreement in judgement betwixt you and us thus far. Neither can we ſee how, upon this conceſſion, you can in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152166:18"/>
finde fault with our proceedings, if there ſhould be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for our cenſuring any ſuch perſons, as for their notorious offences and their obſtinacy therein, might juſtly merit the higheſt cenſure.</p>
            <p>For however, perhaps you may ſay, you ſtumble chiefely at this, that our ruling Elders (that in your judgement may be but meer Lay-men) do joyn in the Government with us; yet we ſee not how this can be any juſt ground of ſcruple to any of you, who (if we miſtake not) were all of you ſatisfied in your conſciences touching the lawfulneſs of the late Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Epiſcopacy, as it was then exerciſed, at leaſt as to ſubmiſſion to it; and wherein High-Commiſſioners, Chancelors and Commiſſaries (that were as much Lay-men then, as ruling Elders can be in your judgement now) had ſo great a ſhare, as to ſuſpend Miniſters from the exerciſe of their Miniſtry, upon ſuch complaints as, according to the orders, that were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in thoſe dayes, they might take cognizance of, and ſo far, as to decree the ſentence of excommunication againſt them and others, as there was occaſion for it.</p>
            <p>But here we muſt yet further profeſs, we do not know, whom you mean by lawfull Paſtors, to whom you here grant the power of excommunication.<note place="margin">Dr Hammond.</note> Some we know, there are, that would make the Dioceſan Biſhops the onely Paſtors of the Church, and that other Miniſters do but officiate by deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them and under them. We hope you are not of the minde of theſe. For then, as the diſſent in judgement betwixt you and us would be far greater, then as yet we apprehend it is; ſo hence it will follow, that, till Prelacy ſhould be reſtored, there muſt not (if you would provide for the ſafety of the perſons and eſtates of them that ſhould mannage the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) be the diſpencing of any Church cenſures at all. For you may eaſily know, that not only by Acts and Ordinances of Parliament before made for the aboliſhing of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and which are confirmed by the late hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advice aſſented unto by his Highneſs <hi>ſect.</hi> 12.) the office and juriſdiction of Dioceſan Biſhops is taken away. But there is yet a further Barre put in againſt Prelacy in the 11. <hi>ſect.</hi> of the aforeſaid humble Advice; where it is expreſly cautioned, (and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152166:18"/>
we judge it was out of a conſcientious mindfulneſs of what had been in thoſe very termes covenanted againſt) that the liberty, that is granted to ſome, be not extended to Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy. And therefore if any Dioceſan Biſhop ſhould exerciſe his juriſdiction, and excommunicate any perſon within this Land, wherein by Authority (as you may ſee afterward) there is alſo an appointment of another Government, we leave it to thoſe, that are learned in the Law to determine, whether ſuch Dioceſan Biſhops would not run themſelves into a <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if you do not reſtrain lawfull Paſtors to theſe onely, our doubt yet is, Whether you mean not onely ſuch Miniſters, as were ordained by Dioceſan Biſhops, excluding thoſe out of the number, that, ſince their being taken away, have been ordained by Presbyters onely?</p>
            <p>If this be your ſenſe, we ſhall onely at preſent minde you, of what is publiſhed, to be the Judgement of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> late Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a Book lately put forth by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> Preacher to the Honourable Society of <hi>Grayes-Inne;</hi> and whom, though a ſtranger to us, and one of a different judgement from us in the point of Epiſcopacy, yet we reverence for his mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and profeſſion of his deſires for peace, <hi>wiſhing that ſuch, as do conſent in ſubſtantials for matter of Doctrine, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of ſome conjunction in point of Diſcipline. That private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and circumſtantials might not keep them thus far aſunder.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See pag. <hi>14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> of his last Book.</note> In which wiſh as we do cordially joyn our ſelves, ſo we hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire, that all godly and moderate ſpirited men throughout the Land would alſo cloſe. But the book, which the ſaid Doctor hath lately publiſhed, is intituled. <hi>The Judgement of the late Archbiſhop of</hi> Armagh <hi>and Primate of</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this Book this Doctor tells us, that the late Primate in Anſwer to a letter of his (ſent to him as it ſhould ſeem for that purpoſe) declares his Judgement touching the ordination of the Miniſtry in the Reformed Churches in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> There he ſaith, that <hi>Epiſcopus &amp; Presbyter gradu tantum differunt, non ordine.</hi> And conſequently, that in places, where Biſhops cannot be had, the ordination by Presbyters ſtandeth valid. And in the cloſe of his Anſwer about this point he ſaith; <hi>That for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152166:19"/>
teſtifiying of his Communion with the Churches</hi> (of the <hi>Low-Countryes</hi>) of whom he had ſpoken immediately before: and which he there profeſſeth, <hi>He doth love and honour as true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Univerſall Church:</hi> (notwithſtanding the difference, that was betwixt him and them about the point of Epiſcopacy) he doth profeſs, <hi>That with like affection he ſhould receive the bleſſed</hi> Sacrament <hi>at the hands of the Dutch Miniſters, if he were in</hi> Holland, <hi>as he ſhould do at the hands of the French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters if, he were in</hi> Charenton. See <hi>pag.</hi> 125. and 126. Hence you may perceive, that the Judgement of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Uſher</hi> was; That the Ordination of Presbyters, where Biſhops cannot be had, ſtandeth valid. And conſequently, if you be of his opinion, (and you muſt have ſtronger reaſons, then ever yet we have ſeen, to bear you out therein if you judge otherwiſe) they ought to be eſteemed lawfull Paſtors, to whom you grant the power of Excommunication, Biſhops being now taken away, and may not therefore ordain according to the preſent Laws of the Land. The ſaid D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> hath ſome animadvertiſements upon that Letter (in which D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Uſher</hi> doth deliver his judgement, as above ſaid) and there ſhews, that he was not in this Judgement of his ſingular. He alledgeth D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Davenant,</hi> that pious and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Biſhop of <hi>Sarisbury,</hi> as conſenting with him in it (in his determinations <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 42.) and produceth the principall of the Schooleman, <hi>Gulielmus Pariſienſis, Gerſon, Durand,</hi> &amp;c. and declares it to be the Generall opinion of the Schoolemen; <hi>Epiſcopatum ut diſtinguitur à ſimplici ſacerdotio non eſſe alium ordinem,</hi> &amp;c. ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 130. of the aforenamed Book, as alſo <hi>pag.</hi> 131.132. Where the concurrence of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Davenant</hi> with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> in his judgement about this matter is declared more fully. He addes alſo others, as in ſpeciall, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Richard Field</hi> in his learned Book of the Church <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. and <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. And alſo that Book intituled <hi>A defence of the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Miniſters of the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, maintained by Archdeacon</hi> Maſon <hi>againſt the Romaniſts.</hi> And further he ſaith; <hi>He hath been aſſured, it was not onely the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of Biſhop</hi> Overall, <hi>but that he had a principall hand in it.</hi> He tell us, <hi>that the fore-mentioned Author produceth many teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; The</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>of the Sentences, and moſt of the Schoolemen,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:152166:19"/>
Bonaventure, Thomas Aquinas, Durand, Dominicus Soto, Richardus Armachanus, Toſtatus, Alphonſus a Caſtro, Gerſon, Petrus Caniſius, <hi>to have affirmed the ſame; and at laſt quoteth</hi> Medina <hi>a principall Biſhop of the Councill of</hi> Trent, <hi>who affirmed, That</hi> Jerome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Sedulius, Primaſius, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, Theodoret, Theophylact <hi>were of the ſame judgment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi> But you may ſee theſe things your ſelves in D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard, pag.</hi> 132, 133, 134. Wee have been onely at the pains to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them.</p>
            <p>Wee could alledg many more Teſtimonies to prove this: But wee count theſe ſufficient; and do alledg theſe the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe brought by one that is of the ſame Judgment with you, as wee ſuppoſe.</p>
            <p>But having declared how farr you accord with us in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, touching the way of informing the ignorant, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the wicked perſons, and ſchiſmatical, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you tell us; <hi>That you are not therein ſo wavering and unſettled in your appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the Caſe, as to ſubmit either it or them, either wholly or in part, to the contrary Judgment and determination of a general Council of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches, much leſſe to a new termed Provincial Aſſembly at</hi> Preſton; <hi>wherein you profeſſe no little to differ from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That, which wee ſubmitted wholly to the Judgment of the Provincial Aſſembly, was not, whether Catechizing was a way appointed by God in his Word, for the information of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; but in what way of Catechizing (as is expreſſed in our Paper) the ignorant in our Congregations, who never offered themſelves unto the Sacrament, were moſt like to be brought to ſome meaſure of knowledg; and which is not a matter of Doctrine but of Order onely. Neither was it by us ſubmitted to that Aſſembly; whether the cenſures of the Church were the means appointed by Chriſt for the reforming of the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous? But whether it might not be meet <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> and as the preſent caſe ſtood, to apply the Cenſures? (and ſo put in practice at this time that, which in the General wee were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently aſſured from the word of Truth, was the way for their reformation) and with which wee were both by God and Man intruſted to diſpenſe unto thoſe that were openly ſcandalous in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152166:20"/>
our Congregations; However they contented themſelves to live in the want of the Lords Supper, nor ever preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Elderſhip to be admitted to it. And this (becauſe meerely circumſtantiall, as to the diſpencing of the Cenſures at this time and to ſuch Perſons) we think herein we owed the Provinciall Aſſembly (unto whoſe Authority we profeſs our ſelves to be ſubject) ſo much reſpect and duty, as to ſubmit our apprehenſions in a Caſe of this nature (which they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto us to be ſeriouſly weighed, as they had done to the reſt of the Claſſes within this Province) unto their Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, and to take their concurrent approvall along with us, before we proceeded to practiſe in a matter of this weight. And yet we have declared before, That however we are not ſo wavering and unſettled in matters of faith, as to reſolve our belief into the determination of <hi>Synods</hi> or Councils, believing no more, nor no otherwiſe, then as they determine: Yet that it is not out of the compaſs of the authority of a <hi>Synod</hi> to examine, try and authoritatively to cenſure Doctrines as well as matters of Diſcipline. And we think (how confident ſoever you may be of the ſoundneſs and orthodoxneſs of what in your Paper you propound in way of exception againſt any thing in ours) you have not ſuch clear and inqueſtionable grounds from Scripture for the ſame, that you were to be accuſed of wavering or unſettledneſs, if you had ſubmitted the ſame to have been examined and tried by a Provincial Aſſembly: and much leſs, if you could have had the opportunity of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to the Cenſure of a General Council.</p>
            <p>But whereas mentioning our Provincial Aſſembly at <hi>Preſton,</hi> you call it a new termed <hi>Provincial Aſſembly.</hi> If your meaning be, that the terming it a Provincial Aſſembly in ſtead of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial <hi>Synod</hi> is a new term, then this is but onely a <hi>Logo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machia,</hi> and not much to be inſiſted on. Although we fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently call it a Provincial <hi>Synod</hi> as well as a Provincial Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. But if your meaning be; <hi>That it is a new termed Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Aſſembly at</hi> Preſton. Becauſe Provinciall <hi>Synods</hi> or Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies have been held but lately at <hi>Preſton,</hi> we ſee not (if Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Aſſemblies be warrantable, and have been of ancient uſe in the Church) that having been long in dis-uſe, they begin of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152166:20"/>
late to be held at <hi>Preſton,</hi> that can juſtly incurre your cenſure. But if the Antiquity of ſuch Aſſemblies be that you queſtion: Then we referre you to what D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> in the Book of his above quoted, ſhews was the Judgement of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> (who is acknowledged by all that knew him, or are acquainted with his works, to have been a great Antiquary; however we alleadge him not, that you ſhould build your faith upon his Teſtimony) and which we think may be ſufficient to vindicate Provincial Aſſemblies in your thoughts from all ſuſpition of novelty. In that Book you have in the cloſe of it propoſals touching the Reduction of Epiſcopacy unto the form of <hi>Synodical</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment received in the ancient Church. And it thus begins. <hi>By the Order of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>all Presbyters are charged to adminiſter the Doctrine and Sacraments, and the Diſcipline of Chriſt, as the Lord hath commanded, and as this Realm hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And that they might the better underſtand, what the Lord hath commanded herein, The exhortation of</hi> Paul <hi>to the Elders of</hi> Epheſus Acts 20.28. <hi>is appointed to be read unto them at the time of their Ordination.</hi> A little after it is acknowledged, <hi>That</hi> Ignatius <hi>by Presbytery mentioned by</hi> Paul 1 Tim. 4.14. <hi>did underſtand the Community of the reſt of the Presbyters or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who then had a hand, not onely in the delivery of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Sacraments, but alſo in the adminiſtration of the Diſcipline of Chriſt.</hi> And for further proof. Tertullian <hi>is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged in his Generall Apologie for Chriſtians. Where he ſaith, that in the Church are uſed exhortations, chaſtiſements and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine cenſure; For Judgement is given with great advice, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe, who are certain, they are in the ſight of God. And it is the chiefeſt foreſhewing of the Judgement to come, if any man have ſo offended, that he be baniſhed from the Communion of Prayer, and of the Aſſembly, and of all holy Fellowſhip. The Preſidents, that bear rule therein, are certain approved Elders, who have obtained this honour, not by reward, but by good report. There alſo is further ſhewed, That in matters of Eccleſiaſtical judicature,</hi> Cornelius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>uſed the received form of gathering together the Presbytery. And that</hi> Cyprian <hi>ſufficiently declares of what Perſons that conſiſted; When he wiſheth him to read his Letter to the flouriſhing Clergy, which there did preſide
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152166:21"/>
or rule with him. And further, That in the</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Council of</hi> Carthage <hi>it was concluded. That the Biſhop might hear no mans cauſe without the preſence of the Clergy. And that otherwiſe the Biſhops ſentence ſhould be void, unleſs it were confirmed by the Clergy. And yet further. That this is found inſerted into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of</hi> Egbert <hi>(who was Archbiſhop of</hi> York <hi>in the</hi> Saxon <hi>times) and afterwards into the body of the Canon law it ſelf. It is here alſo acknowledged, That in our Church, this kind of Presbyterian Government hath been much diſuſed. Yet that it did profeſs, that every Paſtor hath a right to rule the Church (from whence alſo the name of Rector was at firſt given unto him) and adminiſter the Diſcipline of Chriſt, as well as to diſpence the Doctrine and Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. By all which it is acknowledged, and alſo proved; That the form of Government by the united ſuffrages of the Clergy, is ancient: and which is there in expreſs termes aſſerted; as it might be demonſtrated by many more Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but that we conceive theſe already mentioned are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and being alleadged by the aforementioned Author, As alſo evidencing what his own Judgement was in this point, may be more likely to ſway with you (if in that there ſhould be a diſſent betwixt you and us) then any thing, that we could our ſelves produce. But in this reduction of Epiſcopacy to the form of <hi>Synodical</hi> Government received in the ancient Church, there are propoſals of Aſſemblies of Paſtors within certain limited bounds. Which (ſaving that they are ſome of them ſomewhat larger then ours, which is but a circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial difference) do hold proportion with the Claſſical, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, and National Aſſemblies, mentioned in the form of our Church Government. As alſo the times propounded there for their meeting, the power of theſe Aſſemblies, and what they were to have Cognizance of, and the ſubordination of the leſſer to the greater, with liberty of Appeal, if need ſhould require, and are the ſame in ſubſtance as with us. And all theſe were propounded, as the way of Government in the ancient Church, and in the year 1641. (after the troubles, that had riſen in <hi>Scotland</hi> about Epiſcopacy and the Ceremonies, and before the ſetting up of the Presbyterian Government in this Land, had ſo much as fallen under debate in the Parliament,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152166:21"/>
ſo far as ever we heard of) as an expedient to prevent the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that did after ariſe in this Land about the matter of Church Government, being for the moderating of Epiſcopacy; That at that time was grown to that height, that it had quite taken away from the Paſtors that rule, that of right did belong unto them; And for the Reduction of it to the ancient form of <hi>Synodicall</hi> Government. And therefore in the Judgement of this learned and reverend Antiquary, our Provincial Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at <hi>Preſton</hi> (where the Paſtors of the Churches are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as he acknowledgeth of right they ought to be in ſuch Aſſemblies) would not have been accounted a new termed Provincial Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>But you go on and tell us. <hi>That other parts of our Paper are full of darkneſs, to which you ſay, you cannot ſo fully aſſent, till further explicated and unfolded by us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot apprehend any ſuch darkneſs in our Paper, as you ſpeak of. But yet becauſe in yours, you queſtion what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we have from the civil Magiſtrate, for what we do, and likewiſe the extent of it: and your miſtakes of our meaning may perhaps ſome of them ariſe from your unacquaintedneſs with the rule we walk by. Although we were not to be blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for any miſtakes, that might ariſe <hi>ab ignorantia juris</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimple or affected, that we determine not, but leave you to examine;) Before we come to make Anſwer more particularly to what follows, we are willing to be at ſome paines to give you ſome further account of the power we are awarranted by the civil Authority, for to exerciſe. To what perſons within our bounds it extends it ſelf: and what ſome of thoſe rules are, that are preſcribed unto us by civil Authority, to walk by in the exerciſe of that power we are betruſted with.</p>
            <p>It is a general and common miſtake amongſt many, that the Presbyterian Government was eſtabliſhed by the Parliament but for three yeers, and that therefore it is now expired and out of date. But if you peruſe all that paſſed in Parliament touching it, no ſuch matter will appear. <hi>The directions of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, after advice had with the Aſſembly of Divines, for the Electing and chuſing Ruling Elders in all the Congregations, and in the Claſſical Aſſemblies,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152166:22"/>
for the Cities of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and the ſeveral</hi> Counties <hi>of the</hi> Kingdom, <hi>For the ſpeedy ſetling of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Government, bearing date</hi> Auguſt. 19. 1645. <hi>Their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance together with Rules and Directions, concerning ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, in caſes of Ignorance and ſcandall, dated</hi> Octob. 20. 1645. <hi>The Votes alſo of the ſaid Houſes for the Choiſe of Elders throughout the</hi> Kingdom <hi>of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales <hi>in the reſpective Pariſh Churches and Chappels, according to the directions before mentioned. And touching the power granted to the Tryers of Elections of Elders, Of the date of</hi> Feb. 20. 1645. <hi>and</hi> Feb. 26. 1645. <hi>Their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for keeping ſcandalous Perſons from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; the inabling of Congregations for the choice of Elders, and ſupplying of defects in former Ordinances and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Parliament concerning Church Government, bearing date</hi> March 14. 1645. <hi>The Remedies preſcribed by them for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving ſome obſtructions in Church Government, dated</hi> Aprill. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1647. <hi>And their Ordinance for the ſpeedy dividing and ſetling the ſeverall</hi> Counties <hi>of this</hi> Kingdom <hi>into diſtinct Claſſicall Presbyteries and Congregationall Elderſhips, dated</hi> Jan. 29. 1647. We ſay, all theſe were paſſed abſolutely without any provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo's at all, limiting the time of their continuance, that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in any of them. Indeed in the Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giving power to all the Claſſical Presbyteries within their reſpective bounds, to examine, approve and ordain Miniſters for ſeverall Congregations, dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 10. 1645. It is provided in the Cloſe of it, <hi>That it ſhall ſtand in force for twelve moneths, and no longer.</hi> As it is provided in another Ordinance for the Ordination of Miniſters by the Claſſicall Presbyters within their reſpective bounds for the ſeverall Congregations in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of, <hi>England</hi> bearing date <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 28. 1646. <hi>That it ſhall ſtand in force for three years and no longer.</hi> Which latter might give to ſome (that took but the matter upon report) an occaſion to conceive, that the Presbyterian Government was ſettled but for three years. Although that was but ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to all the ſeverall Ordinances that had paſſed before, which belonged onely to one. But the Ordinance eſpecially, from which chiefely (as we conceive) the miſtake aroſe about
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152166:22"/>
ſettling the Presbyterian Government for three years onely, was the Ordinance that paſſed <hi>June</hi> 5. 1646. The title where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, <hi>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, for the preſent ſettling (without further delay) of the Presbyteriall Government in the Church of</hi> England. In the Cloſe whereof it is ordained. <hi>That this Ordinance ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for the ſpace of three years, and no longer, unleſs both Houſes think fit to continue it. But if the matter of this Ordinance be conſulted, it is manifeſt it was but touching a Committee of Lords and Commons to adjudge and determine ſcandalous offences not formerly enumerated, appointed by the Ordinance in ſtead and place of Commiſſioners mentioned in the Ordinance of</hi> March 14. 1645. <hi>And alſo ſhewing how the Elderſhips were to proceed in the examination of ſuch ſcandalous offences. And touching what power was granted to the ſaid Committee, and in what ſort they were to proceed, as is clear to any, that ſhall but take the paines to peruſe that Ordinance.</hi> The ground whereof in the preface to it, is made to be this. <hi>The Lords and Commons in Parliament holding their former reſolution, that all notorious and ſcandalous offenders ſhall be kept from the Sacrament, have thought fit to make a further addition to the ſcandalous offences formerly enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated, for which men ſhall be kept back from the Sacrament. And leaſt the ſtay of the enumeration, and the not naming of Commiſſioners to judge of Caſes not enumerated, ſhould hinder the putting in execution the Presbyterian Governement already eſtabliſhed, They have thought fit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And do therefore ordain a Committee (therein particularly nominated) in ſtead and place of Commiſſioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The groundleſneſs of the miſtake about ſettling the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Government for three years onely, that might ariſe from the proviſo in this Ordinance, is ſo clear to any common underſtanding, that the bare recitall of the ſum of the matter of this Ordinance, and the ground of making it, doth make it ſo fully to appear, that it were but loſt labour to uſe any more words about it. But we have particularly mentioned all that ever paſſed the Parliament (ſo far as we have either ſeen or heard of) that hitherto concerned Church Government, untill the year 1648. <hi>When the form of Church Government to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152166:23"/>
be uſed in the Church of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>was agreed upon by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, after Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice had with the Aſſembly of Divines, and was ordered by them to be printed</hi> Auguſt. 19. <hi>of the ſaid</hi> year 1648. And this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (wherein all that had paſſed the Parliament before in parts, and at ſeverall times, and what ever was but temporary, by vertue of other Ordinances (ſo far as was intended for continuance) are moulded up into a complete body, with a ſupply of ſundry things that had been never mentioned nor publiſhed before in other Ordinances) is without any limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time for its continuance, and remains unrepealed to this day, for any thing we have ſeen or heard to the contrary. Nay we think (as we ſhall touch upon anon) That by the humble Advice, aſſented to by his Highneſs, this Ordinance (as well as others) receives ſtrength.</p>
            <p>But by this full account given, we think we have made it ſufficiently to appear, that we have had the Authority of the civill Magiſtrate to bear us out, in what we have acted ſince the firſt ſetting up of the Presbyterian Government untill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Except there be any, that can come forth, and charge us to have tranſgreſſed the rules appointed by the Parliament for us to obſerve in our actings, againſt which our own inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency only ſhall be our defence.</p>
            <p>It now remaines for your further ſatisfaction and our own vindication, that we recite ſome things particularly out of the form of Church Government, which we conceive are thereunto ſubſervient.</p>
            <p>In the very firſt Words of the Ordinance (according to what we have before recited in the directions for the electing and chooſing of ruling Elders, and is there alſo to be found) you may find it thus. <hi>Be it ordered and ordained by the Lords and Commons in Parliament Aſſembled and by Authority of the ſame, That all Pariſhes and Places whatſoever within the</hi> Kingdom <hi>of</hi> England <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>(as well Priviledged Places and exempted juriſdictions, as others) be brought under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Congregationall, Claſſicall, Provinciall and Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Aſſemblies,</hi> &amp;c. Where it is to us unqueſtionable, That by vertue of this appointment, ſuch as live within the bounds
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152166:23"/>
of our ſeverall congregations and Pariſhes are under the power of ſome one or other of the Congregational Elderſhips, conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Authority of Parliament within our ſeverall Pariſhes; And that all thoſe, that live within the bounds of our Claſſis (mentioned before) are under the power of our Claſſicall Aſſembly, conſtituted in like manner by the ſaid Authority.</p>
            <p>What power is given particularly to the congregationall El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhips, you may finde in the aforeſaid form of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and unto which we refer you; onely we ſhall minde you, <hi>That by vertue thereof, they have power, as they ſhall ſee juſt occaſion, to enquire into the knowledge and ſpirituall eſtate of any member of the Congregation to admoniſh, and rebuke, to ſuſpend from the Lords Table, thoſe who are found by them, to be ignorant and ſcandalous, and to excommunicate according to the rules and directions after following.</hi> And it is thereby or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, <hi>That the Examination and Judgement of ſuch Perſons, as ſhall for their ignorance in the points of Religion, mentioned in that Ordinance, not be admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, is to be in the power of the Elderſhip of every Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> All which will appear by the expreſs Letter of the ſaid Ordinance, to any, that will conſult it, and which not only juſtifies all that is practiſed in that caſe by the ſeverall Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, but alſo ſhews what grounds this Claſſis had for that which was mentioned in our Paper, touching both what is therein appointed to the Miniſter about Catechizing Families, and alſo concerning the Miniſters exhorting ſuch, as in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Families he ſhould finde to be of competent knowledge, and know to be of blameleſs life, That they ſhould preſent themſelves to the Elderſhip; The Triall and Judgement in this caſe not belonging to any one Miniſter alone, but to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip.</p>
            <p>There are alſo rules and directions given in this Ordinance to be obſerved by the ſeverall Elderſhips, concerning ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper in caſes of ſcandall, which may be ſeen there particularly. But there is no rule gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that will allow either the Elderſhip or Claſſis, according to the ſeveral powers to them therein granted, either to warn before all, or to excommunicate knowing and blameleſs men
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152166:24"/>
for their meer not preſenting themſelves before the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>The rules of this Government preſcribe otherwiſe; as we our ſelves muſt alſo needs profeſs, that we are not conſcious to our ſelves, that we have given any juſt occaſion by our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof, That contrary to the expreſs rules appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein to be obſerved by us, and to the plain ſenſe of our expreſſions uſed in our Paper (of which afterward,) any ſuch a thing ſhould have been ſo much as ſuppoſed to have been intended from any thing there expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Give us leave to proceed a little further, to lay open the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that is preſcribed in the above mentioned form of Church Government, touching the order of proceeding to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; which as it will awarrant the publiſhing of mens names openly in the Congregation, and warning them before all to reform, being ſuch as are juſtly cenſurable by the rules there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and particularly where it preſcribes, <hi>that ſeveral publique admonitions ſhall be given to the offenders,</hi> &amp;c. So it will awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant us in any thing, that is made cenſurable by that Paper of ours, that was publiſhed.</p>
            <p>To make this to appear, as alſo to ſhew what reaſon, we had to make known to the ſeveral congregations within our bounds, what our Paper held forth. We ſhall here declare, what offences are cenſurable with this greateſt and laſt cenſure of Excommunication, according to the order, that is there preſcribed, and which, as it requires, <hi>that it be inflicted with great and mature deliberation, and after all other good means have been eſſayed;</hi> ſo it appoints in theſe expreſs Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſuch Errours in practice as ſubvert the Faith, or any other Errours, which overthrow the power of Godlineſs; if the party who holds them, ſpread them, ſeeking to draw others after him; and ſuch ſins in practice, as cauſe the Name and Truth of God to be blaſphemed, cannot ſtand with the power of godlineſs; and ſuch practiſes, as in their own nature manifeſtly ſubvert that order, unity and Peace, which Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in his Church; and particularly all thoſe ſcandalous ſins, for which any Perſon is to be ſuſpended from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perſiſted in; theſe being publiquely known, to the juſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152166:24"/>
of the Church; The ſentence of Excommunication may and ought to proceed, according to the directions after following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Perſons, that hold other Errours in Judgement, about which learned and Godly men poſſibly may and do differ, and which ſubvert not the faith, nor are deſtructive to godlineſs, or that be guilty of ſuch ſins of infirmities, as are commonly found in the Children of God: or being otherwiſe found in the faith, and holy in life (and ſo not falling under cenſure by the former rules) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of Peace; and do yet out of conſcience, not come up to the obſervation of all thoſe rules, which are or ſhall be eſtabliſhed by Authority, for regulating the outward worſhip of God, and Government of his Church. The ſentence of excommunication for theſe cauſes ſhall not be denounced againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things this Claſſis taking into Conſideration, together with the power they were betruſted with by God and Man, for the diſpencing the cenſures of the Church, in the caſes cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable by the rules here laid down and elſewhere, in the form of Church Government: And there having been in the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Aſſembly ſeverall debates touching ſuch Perſons as in the ſeveral Congregations were ignorant and ſcandalous, who offered not themſelves to the Sacrament, not to the Elderſhip in order to their admiſſion to it: and they commending it to the ſeveral Claſſical Presbyteries to be conſidered of, whether ſome further courſe was not to be held, for the information of the one, and the reformation of the other, then yet had been taken, notwithſtanding their neglect; and what they judged fitteſt to be done for the attaining thoſe ends; and to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their thoughts therein to the next Aſſembly. This Claſſis upon the whole concluded to repreſent their apprehenſions in the Caſe, as is expreſſed in the Paper that was publiſhed, which was approved of before by the Provincial Aſſembly, and which they judge is ſufficiently awarranted, in regard of any thing therein contained, by the rules expreſſed in the above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned form of Church Government.</p>
            <p>We having thus far ſhewed what we have been, and are awarranted to practice by the ſeveral Ordinances above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, we ſhall now proceed further to declare. That how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152166:25"/>
we are no Lawyers, and therefore leave the determination of the Caſe to the learned in the Law to judge of, to whom it belongs: yet if it may be lawfull for us to judge of a matter of this nature from the principles of reaſon; It ſeems to us, that the above mentioned Ordinances about Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well as other Ordinances of Parliament, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the humble Advice aſſented unto by his Highneſs in the 16. ſection thereof. Where we finde theſe Words. <hi>And that nothing contained in this Petition and Advice, nor your Highneſs conſent thereunto, ſhall be conſtrued to extend to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing or making void of any Act or Ordinance, which is not contrary hereunto, or to the matters herein contained. But that the ſaid Acts and Ordinances, not contrary hereunto, ſhall continue and remain in force, in ſuch manner, as if this preſent Petition and Advice had not at all been had or made, or your Highneſs conſent thereunto given.</hi> Whence we gather, that if in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ordinances for Church Government, there be nothing contrary to the humble Advice, or to the matters therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, they are not thereby (any more then any other Acts or Ordinances of Parliament) repealed, but left to remain in force. At leaſt, there ſeems to us to be a plain intimation, that they have a force in them, which is not by this humble Advice repealed and made void. For it doth not appear to us, That there is any thing in the Form of Church Government, or any other Ordinances of Parliament about that matter; that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the humble Advice or matters therein contained. And whereas in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſection there is mention made of ſome that differ in worſhip and diſcipline from the publique profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe Nations held forth, to whom ſome indulgence is granted; It ſeems to us, there is an acknowledgement and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what the late Parliament held forth, in regard of theſe the Directory for worſhip and form of Church Government, which they paſſed, as the publique profeſſion of theſe Nations in regard of worſhip and diſcipline. And in which apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions we are the more confirmed, becauſe here in this ſection, mention is made of a confeſſion of faith to be agreed on by his Highneſs and the Parliament, there having nothing in that kind paſſed the late Parliament, that eſtabliſhed the Directory
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152166:25"/>
for worſhip and form of Church Government. However there had been a Confeſſion of faith drawn up by the late Aſſembly of Divines; Whence it ſeems to us clear, that they own the Directory for worſhip, and the form of Church Government, to be that which they hold forth, as the publique profeſſion of the Nation for worſhip and Government. To the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we find in the Government of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. As it was publiquely declared at <hi>Weſtminſter Decemb.</hi> 16. 1653. <hi>pag.</hi> 43. <hi>Sect.</hi> 37. <hi>Where alſo they expreſs a worſhip and Diſcipline publiquely held forth, which muſt needs referre to the Directory and form of Church Government by us recited;</hi> There being no other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or diſcipline, that then had, or now hath, the civill San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in this Nation.</p>
            <p>We have been large, in what we have here repreſented in the generall, before we come to ſpeak more particularly to the reſt, that now follows in your Paper. But our pains being greater to make this full repreſentation unto you, then it will be for you to read it, we muſt intreat you to excuſe us, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it tends as well to rectifie your miſtakes, as to vindicate our ſelves, being alſo deſirous not to be miſtaken any more, as alſo becauſe it layes a foundation for our briefer and more particular Anſwer unto what follows, and to which (theſe things being thus premiſed) we now come.</p>
            <p>In the things, wherein you profeſs your ſelves to diſſent, till further explicated and unfolded by us.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The firſt thing we meet with here is; That by the many Perſons of all ſorts, that are members of Congregations, and mentioned in our Paper, in your ſenſe thereof we ſeem to hint, that thereby we mean onely ſuch, <hi>who have admitted themſelves members of ſome Congregation within our aſſociation, and yet live inordinately;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that therefore you, who never were any members or aſſociates of ours, are not within the verge and compaſs of our Presbyterian diſcipline,</hi> &amp;c. Unto which we ſay; That we have conſtantly profeſſed againſt thoſe of the ſeparation. That the ſeveral Aſſemblies of Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within this Land, that make a profeſſion of the true Chriſtian and Apoſtolique Faith, are true Churches of Jeſus
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152166:26"/>
Chriſt. That the ſeveral members of theſe Congregations are by their birth, members, as thoſe that were born in the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh Church, are ſaid to be, by the Apoſtle, Jews by nature: <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. That this their memberſhip was ſealed to them in their Baptiſm, that did ſolemnly admit them, as into the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, ſo into the particular, wherein they were born. We have alſo conſtantly maintained againſt the afore mentioned Perſons; That the Miniſters of theſe Churches are true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, notwithſtanding that exception of theirs againſt them, that they were ordained by Biſhops, who alſo themſelves were true Miniſters in our Judgement (though we cannot acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that by divine right they were ſuperiour to their fellow brethren, either in regard of order or juriſdiction) And that therefore the Word and Sacraments (the moſt eſſential marks of a true viſible Church, according to the profeſſed Judgement of our Divines againſt the Papiſts on the one hand, and thoſe of the ſeparation on the other) diſpenſed by theſe Miniſters, were, and are the true Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt. And that hereupon our work was not (when the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was appointed) to conſtitute Churches, but to reform them onely. And that therefore none within our bounds, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they ſhall renounce Chriſtianity and their Baptiſm, can be deemed by us to be without, in the Apoſtles ſenſe; and ſo therefore not within the compaſs and verge of our Presbyterian Government. Neither is it their not aſſociating with us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Government, that doth exempt them from cenſure by it, if they ſhould be ſuch offenders, as by the rules thereof were juſtly cenſurable. It not being a matter arbitrary, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons at their own will and pleaſure to exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from under that Eccleſiaſtical Government, that is ſetled by Authority. And as you know it would not have been allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of under the former Government.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) And therefore whether you, and all others within our bounds, be not comprehended within our Government, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules laid down in the Ordinance of Parliament above mentioned, appointing the form of Church Government to be uſed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and therein ordaining, as hath been recited before in the firſt page thereof,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152166:26"/>
and to which we refer you. (Eſpecially conſidering, that all within the bounds of our ſeveral Pariſhes (that are no other now them formerly) even Papiſts and Anabaptiſts and other Sectaries, were under the late Prelatical Government) we leave it to you to judge. Onely if ſo, we wiſh you to conſider, that then you are brought under the Government of Presbytery, not ſo much by us, as by the Parliament appointing this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And then we think you, who warn us not to contemn civil power, might well (out of reſpect to the Authority or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining it, but eſpecially conſidering the word Presbytery is a known Scripture expreſſion 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and interpreted by ſundry of the Fathers, as we do, as hath been declared before) have uſed a more civil expreſſion, then to have called it a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fold, into which (it ſhould ſeem) your complaint is, that you ſhould be driven. Although Presbytery layes reſtraint on none, but ſuch as being ſcandalous in their lives, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the Laws of God, are therefore truely and indeed the lawleſs Perſons, that we ſpeak of. But whereas (as you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) <hi>This is our chief deſign in this, as in other tranſactions of ours, to ſubject all to our Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do refer our ſelves to our courſe of life paſt, and hope it will witneſs with us, to all that will judge impartially, what our deſigns have been in our other tranſactions. And as touching our deſign in the Paper publiſhed, whether it hath been ought but the information of the ignorant, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſcandalous, to the Glory of God and their ſalvation, we leave it to be judged by thoſe, that will judge of mens intentions by what is expreſſed in their words and actions.</p>
            <p>We know very well, we are charged by ſome, that we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Dominion, to Lord it over the People, and to have all ſorts of Perſons, of what rank ſoever, to ſtoop to us. But we do openly profeſs, that the Government of the Church, that is committed unto men, is not Deſpotical, but Miniſterial. That it is no Dominion, but a Miniſtery onely. And that the Officers, that are intruſted with it, are themſelves to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, both in regard of their bodies and eſtates, to the Civil power: That by the Ordinance of God, they are appointed to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152166:27"/>
be under, and that in their Government they have nothing to do with the bodies and eſtates of any Perſons, but with their Souls onely. Although here we deſire to enquire of you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if you be indeed for the ſettling of any Government at all in the Church (as you profeſs to be) you do not think, that all ſhould be ſubject to it? We cannot judge you to be ſo irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, as to be for a Government, and that yet ſubjection to it muſt be denyed. And if the late Government of the Prelacy was not blamed by you, becauſe it required ſubjection to it; we wiſh you to conſider, whether upon this account you have reaſon to cenſure us. But further, whereas you tell us; <hi>That we garniſh our Government with the ſpecious title of Chriſts Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Throne and Scepter.</hi> We wiſh you to conſider, what in your Anſwer to an objection (that you frame out of our Paper) your ſelves do ſay. You there tell us. <hi>You pray for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch Church Government, as is conſonant to the will of God, and univerſall practice of primitive Churches. That Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline may be exerciſed in the hands of them, to whom it was committed by Chriſt, and left by him to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from hand to hand to the end of the World.</hi> The expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you here uſe, are as high touching that Government you would have eſtabliſhed, as any have been, that ever we have uſed of ours. For your prayer is, <hi>That Eccleſiaſtical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline may be exerciſed in the hands of them, to whom it was committed by Chriſt, and left by him to be transferred from hand to hand to the end of the world.</hi> The Government then, that you are for, muſt be with you, Chriſts Government Throne and Scepter. And why do you then condemn us, if we have uſed ſuch expreſſions concerning our Government, till you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced us, that it is not ſuch? When yet you take to your ſelves the Liberty to uſe the like language, concerning the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you pray may be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But whereas you ſay, Presbytery is the main thing driven at here, and that however ſhe comes uſhered in with Godly pretence of ſorrow for the ſins and the ignorance of the times, and the duty incumbent upon us, to exerciſe the power that Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us, for edification and not for deſtruction, and that theſe are but ſo many waſte Papers, wherein Presbytery is wrapped up
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152166:27"/>
to make it look more handſomely and paſs more currantly.</hi> We do earneſtly deſire, That in the examination of your conſciences, you would ſeriouſly conſider, whether you have not both tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the rules of Charity in paſſing ſuch hard cenſures upon us, and alſo uſurped that, which belongs not to you, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your ſelves judges of what fals not under your cognizance. The things you mention belonging only to be tried by your and our Maſter, to whom we muſt all ſtand or fall. <hi>But we are heartily ſorry, that Presbytery (which ſtands in no need of any painting or cover to make it look more handſomely and paſſe more currantly) ſhould be accounted by you the</hi> anguis in herba, whereof you had need to beware, it having never given that offence to any, as to merit ſuch language.</p>
            <p>But now you frame an objection out of our Paper, and return your Anſwer, profeſſing, <hi>That you pray for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch Church Government throughout his Highneſs Dominions, as is conſonant to the will of God and univerſall practice of primitive Churches,</hi> &amp;c. In that you do here joyn the will of God and the univerſal practiſe of primitive Churches together, as you joyned the Word of God and the conſtant practiſe of the Catholique Church before, you ſeem to us, to make up the rule (whereby we muſt judge what Government it is, that you pray might be eſtabliſhed) of theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi> the will of God and the univerſal practiſe of primitive Churches. Or that it is the univerſal practiſe of primitive Churches. That muſt be our ſure guide and comment upon the Word of God, to tell us, what is his will revealed theſe touching Church Government and diſcipline. If this be your ſenſe (as we apprehend it is) we muſt needs profeſs, that herein we greatly differ from you, as not conceiving it to be ſound and orthodoxe. It being the Word of God alone, and the approved practiſe of the Church recorded there (whether it was the univerſall and conſtant practiſe of the Church or no) that is to be the onely rule to judge by in this, or any other contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies in matters of Religion. But yet admitting for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the rule you ſeem to make, we ſhould deſire to know from you, what that Church Government is, which is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the will of God and univerſall practiſe of primitive Churches. For our own parts, we think it will be very hard
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152166:28"/>
for you, or any others, to demonſtrate out of any Records of Antiquity, what was the univerſall practiſe of primitive Churches for the whole ſpace of the firſt 300. years after Chriſt, or the greateſt part thereof (excepting ſo much as is left upon record in the Scriptures of the new Teſtament) the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Antiquity, that concerne thoſe times (for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of them) being both imperfect, and far from ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, what was the univerſall practiſe of the Church then (though the practiſes of ſome Churches may be mentioned,) and likewiſe very queſtionable. At leaſt it will not be eaſie to aſſure us, that ſome of thoſe, that go under the names of the moſt approved Authors of thoſe times, are neither ſpurious nor corrupted. And hereupon it will unavoidably follow, that we ſhall be left very doubtfull, what Government it is, that is moſt conſonant to the univerſall and conſtant practiſe of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches for that time. But as touching the rule it ſelf, which you ſeem here to lay down, we cannot cloſe with it. We do much honour and reverence the primitive Churches; But yet we believe we owe more reverence to the Scriptures, then to judge them either imperfect or not to have light enough in themſelves, for the reſolving all doubts touching matters of faith or practiſe, except it be firſt reſolved what was either the concurrent interpretation of the Fathers, or the univerſall and conſtant practiſe of the Churches of thoſe times. Beſides that admitting this for a rule, that the univerſall and conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the primitive Churches muſt be that, which muſt aſſure us what is the will of God revealed in Scripture concerning the Government which he hath appointed in the Church, our faith is hereupon reſolved into a moſt uncertain ground, and ſo made fallible and turned into opinion. For what monuments of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, beſides the Scripture, can aſſure us touching the matters of fact therein contained, that they were ſuch indeed, as they are there reported to be? the Authors of them themſelves being men that were not infallibly guided by the Spirit. But yet ſuppoſing we could be infallibly aſſured (which yet never can be) what was the univerſall and conſtant practiſe of the primitive Churches, how ſhall that be a rule to aſſure us, what is moſt conſonant to the will of God? When as we ſee not,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152166:28"/>
eſpecially in ſuch matters, as are not abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation,<note place="margin">Even as a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councill it ſelf is ſubject to errrour.</note> but that the univerſall practiſe of the Churches might in ſome things be diſſonant to the will of God revealed in Scriptures. And ſo the univerſall practiſe of primitive Churches can be no certain rule to judge by, what Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is moſt conſonant to the will of God revealed in his Word. We know there are corruptions in the beſt of men: There was ſuch hot contention betwixt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> as cauſed them to part aſunder. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo failed in his practiſe, as that though before ſome came from <hi>James,</hi> he did eat with the Gentils, yet when they were come he withdrew himſelf, fearing them of the Circumciſion. And hereupon not only other Jews diſſembled with him, but <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo was carried away with their diſſimulation. Whence it's clear, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the beſt men even in thoſe things, wherein they went contrary to the rule of Gods Word, are of a ſpreading nature, and the better the Perſons, that give the bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are, the greater the danger of the more univerſall lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening. Nay we finde, that not only ſome few Apoſtolicall men had their failings, but even Apoſtolicall primitive Churches did, in the very face of the Apoſtles, they being yet alive, make great defection, both in regard of opinions and practiſes. As from the examples of the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> and the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> is manifeſt. The Apoſtle alſo tels us, that even in his time, the myſtery of iniquity began to work: And in after times we know, how the Doctrine was corrupted: what groſs ſuperſtition crept into the Church: what domination was ſtriven for amongſt the Paſtors and Biſhops of the Churches. Till at length Antichriſt was got up into his ſeat, unto which height yet he came not all at once, but by ſteps and degrees. Beſides it is of freſh remembrance, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the reformation happily brought about in our own Church in regard of Doctrine and worſhip, after thoſe diſmall <hi>Marian</hi> times, yet the corruption, in regard of Government continued ſuch, during the time of the late Prelacy (which yet was taken away in other reformed Churches) that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors were deprived of that power of rule, that our Church acknowledgeth did belong to them of right; and which did
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152166:29"/>
anciently belong to them; however the exerciſe thereof did after grow into a long diſuſe, as hath been ſhewed before. And therefore when we conſider on the one hand, that the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority, which the Biſhop obtained at the firſt above the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter in the ancient Church (and which was rather obtained <hi>conſuetudine Eccleſiae</hi> then by Divine right) did at the length grow to that height, that the Paſtors were ſpoiled of all power of rule: ſo we cannot much wonder on the other hand, that the ruling Elder was quite turned out of doors; For the proof of the being and exerciſe of whoſe office in the purer times, there are notwithſtanding produced teſtimonies of the ancients, by Divines both at home and abroad, that have written about that ſubject, and to which we do therein refer you: As there do remain ſome footſteps and ſhadow of their office in the Church-wardens and Sides-men even to this day. And ſo upon the whole, the premiſſes conſidered, and that we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to follow a multitude to do evill (though it were of the beſt of men) and that therefore the examples and practiſes, though it were of whole Churches, are to be no farther a rule for us, then they follow Chriſt, and as their examples be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of in the Word of Chriſt, notwithſtanding the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality and long continuedneſs of ſuch practiſes. Whereas you ſay, <hi>that you pray for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is conſonant to the will of God and univerſall practiſe of primitive Churches;</hi> we believe you might cut the matter a great deal ſhorter, and ſay, That you are for the eſtabliſhing of that Government, that is moſt conſonant to the will of God revealed in the Scriptures, and that the Word of God alone (and on which onely Faith muſt be built, and into which at laſt be reſolved, when other records of Antiquity, that yet are not ſo ancient, as it is, have been ſearcht into never ſo much) ſhall determine what that is, and ſo thoſe weariſome and endleſs diſputes, about what is the univerſall and conſtant practiſe of primitive Churches (and which if it could be found out in any good meaſure of probability for the firſt 300. years after Chriſt, could never yet be ſo farr iſſued, as to be a ſure bottom, whereon our faith may ſafely reſt) may be cut off. It being a moſt certain rule, and eſpecially in matters of faith,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152166:29"/>
that the <hi>Factum</hi> is not to preſcribe againſt the <hi>Jus;</hi> The <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> againſt the <hi>Right</hi> or what ought to be done. And it being out of all queſtion the ſafeſt courſe for all, to bring all doctrine and practices to the ſure and infallible Standard and Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the Word of God alone. And after you have more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly weighed the matter, and remember how you profeſſe, that in the matters you propoſe in your Paper, <hi>You reſt not in the Judgment or determination of any general Council of the Eaſtern or Weſtern Churches, determining contrary, to what you are perſwaded is ſo fully warranted in the Word of God, as well as by the conſtant practice of the Catholick Church;</hi> (although what that was, were more likely to be reſolved by a general Council then by your ſelves) the propoſal of having the Word of God alone to be the Judg of the Controverſie about Church-Government, cannot (wee think) in reaſon be deny'd by you.</p>
            <p>And wee with you ſhall heartily pray, That the Church-Government, which is moſt conſonant to the will of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in Scriptures, might be eſtabliſhed in theſe Lands. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee muſt alſo profeſſe, that wee believe, that that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which is eſtabliſhed by Authority, and which wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, is, for the ſubſtantials of it, this Government, &amp; which wee judg alſo to be moſt conſonant to the practice of the primitive Churches in the pureſt times. And therefore as there was ſome entrance made by the late Parliament, in regard of eſtabliſhing this Government by Ordinances, as the Church-Government of theſe Nations: And as to the putting thoſe Ordinances in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, there hath been ſome beginning in the Province of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Province of this County, and in ſome other places throughout the Land: So when there ſhall be the opportunity offered, wee ſhall not be wanting by petitioning or otherwayes to uſe our beſt endeavors, that it may be fully ſettled through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe Lands. That ſo wee may not, as to Government in the Church, any longer continue as a City without walls, and a Vineyard without an hedg, and ſo (to the undoing of our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) endanger Religion to be quite loſt. And upon which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration wee do earneſtly deſire, that all conſcientious and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſpirited men throughout the Land, though of different principles, whether of the Epiſcopal or Congregational way,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152166:30"/>
would bend themſelves ſo farr as poſſibly they can to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date with us in point of practice: In which there was ſo good a progreſſe made by the late Aſſembly, as to thoſe that were for the Congregational way: And, as wee think, alſo all thoſe that were for the lawfulneſſe of ſubmiſſion to the Government of the late Prelacy, as it was then exerciſed: And that are of the Judgment of the lare Primate of <hi>Ireland</hi> in his reduction of Epiſcopacy unto the form of Synodical Government, (mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before) might do, if they would come up towards us ſo farr, as wee judg their principles would allow them: As wee do alſo profeſſe, that however wee cannot conſent to part with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder, unleſſe wee ſhould betray the truth of Chriſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. (as wee judge,) and dare not give any like conſent to admit of a moderate Epiſcopacy, for fear of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon the Paſtors right, and whereof late ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience leſſons us to beware, as wee judg alſo, that the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of a Biſhop above a Presbyter in degree (which ſome maintain) is no Apoſtolical inſtitution, and ſo have the greater reaſon in that reſpect to caution againſt it: Yet wee do here profeſſe, wee ſhould ſo farr, as will conſiſt with our principles and the peace of our own conſciences, be ready to abate or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate much for peace ſake. That ſo at the length all parties throughout the Land, that have any ſoundneſſe in them in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, and that are ſober and godly, though of different judgments in leſſer matters, being weary of their diviſions, might fall in the necks one of another with mutual embraces and kiſſes, and ſo at laſt (through the tender mercy of our God, there might be an happy cloſure of breaches, and reſtoring of peace and union in this poor, unſettled, rent, and diſtracted Church, to the glory of God throughout all the Churches.</p>
            <p>But now as to you, and what follows in your Paper, (and in the mean ſeaſon, till this can be accompliſhed, and for which wee ſhall heartily pray) wee cannot but judg, that ſuch as are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our bounds, <hi>and live as lawleſſe perſons contemning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, and ſo out of their rank and order,</hi> (and of which ſort you deny not, but that there may be ſome among us, however they be ſubject to Law, and the puniſhment of the Civil Sword, as needs they muſt be) yet being ſuch as are juſtly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152166:30"/>
cenſurable, according to the rules of our Government, wee do not think they are thereby exempted from being reached by that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Sword,</hi> as you phraſe it, which both God and the Civil Authority hath intruſted us with.</p>
            <p>And as wee are farr from contemning the Authority of the Civil Magiſtrate, and ſhall therefore (out of due reſpect unto it, and that the lawleſſe might be curbed) be ready, not onely our ſelves, as wee have a call; but alſo warn others, as there may be occaſion, to make complaint to the Civil Power, that ſo ſuch offenders, being puniſhed by corporal and pecuniary mulcts, to the ſuppreſſion of wickedneſſe and licentiouſneſſe, and the <hi>Reformation of mens lives and maners;</hi> Yet wee do not apprehend why this ſhould hinder us from <hi>warning the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our ſeveral Congregations to make complaint to the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of thoſe, that walk diſorderly and will not be reclaimed, to the end they may be further dealt with, as the nature of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence may deſerve.</hi> Wee being fully aſſured from the word of truth, That Excommunication is Gods ordinance, appointed for the reformation of the ſcandalous, and as you your ſelves acknowledged in the beginning of your Paper: and being a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual puniſhment for the nature and kinde of it, through the bleſſing of God, may be more available for the deſtruction of the fleſh, and the thorough humiliation of the offender, then any corporal or pecuniary mulct (that reaches but the outward man) can be; And as it was bleſſed with great ſucceſſe for this end for many years together, whileſt the Church was deſtitute of Chriſtian Magiſtrates: Although in a Chriſtian State wee ſee not, why wee ſhould divide what God hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wee having not yet learned either from the Scriptures or ſound reaſon, that the conjunction of the Civil and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sword is not more likely, through the ſame bleſſing of God, to work a greater reformation in mens lives, then either of them alone, remembring that old Maxime, <hi>Vis unita fortior.</hi> And as touching our ſelves, and the power wee are intruſted to exerciſe, wee ſhall commit our endeavors unto his bleſſing, in the uſe of his own appointed means who is able, and wee doubt not but hee will, make the ſame effectual for the ends for which hee hath appointed them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152166:31"/>But you ſay, <hi>There are other parts of our Paper, that do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe remain dark, which you deſire to be made plain.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee conceive not ſo of them, yet wee ſhall as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly go along with you, to give you further anſwer, as you to deſire the ſame of us.</p>
            <p>And therefore whereas wee having ſaid in our Paper, <hi>That there are many perſons of all ſorts, that will not ſubmit themſelves to the preſent Government of the Church.</hi> Your firſt Quaere thereupon is, <hi>Why Government in ſingulari?</hi> Wee anſwer, becauſe it is the onely Government, that at preſent is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Church by Civil Authority; The Prelatical being put down, and cautioned againſt in the humble Advice, in regard of any liberty to be extended to it for the exerciſe thereof: And there being no other Government but the Presbyterian (which is our Government) that is owned (as the Church-Government for the whole Nation) by the Civil Authority. And as it is that, which wee judg to be moſt agreeable to the will of God, ſo alſo wee conceive, that whatever is of Chriſts preſcribing in any other different Government (whether Epiſcopal or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational) is to be found here: As wee do apprehend the redundancies of them both to be taken away in this, and the defects of them both to be here ſupplyed. And however there may be differences amongſt godly men concerning Church-Government, which it is that Chriſt <hi>in particulari</hi> hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his Word, yet wee judg that the Government which Chriſt hath preſcribed in his Word is but one; As all thoſe muſt ſay ſo too, that not being Eraſtians do hold, That one Church-Government or other is of divine Right.</p>
            <p>But whereas you bring in <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaying, <hi>Scimus enim unicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Eccleſiae, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this wee ſay; The circumſtantials of Government, that are but matters of order onely, and which muſt be ſuited to the time, or place, or perſons, for whom they are made, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which (if you had quoted the place where <hi>Calvin</hi> uſeth theſe words) wee believe it would appear hee ſpeaks; theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing variable, and ſo but the accidentals of Government, may not be one and the ſame in all Churches. But if Chriſt have preſcribed a Government in his word; for the ſubſtantials of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152166:31"/>
it, it muſt needs be <hi>de jure</hi> one &amp; the ſame in every Church. And that the Presbyterian Government is that in particular, which is there preſcribed, in <hi>Calvins</hi> judgment, is ſo manifeſt by his works to the whole Chriſtian world, that it needs no proof. But if the Government, which Chriſt hath preſcribed, for the ſubſtantials of it be onely one, then that alone is good, and all other Governments differing ſubſtantially from it muſt needs be bad; and this onely <hi>jure divino,</hi> and Chriſts own Government, and the reſt not.</p>
            <p>And therefore, whereas in the next place you ſuppoſe, <hi>Wee may aſſert, that our Government, is the Government by way of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency, as Chriſts own Government, more immediately, and</hi> jure divino. To this and to what you further hereupon do inquire, wee ſay, wee have declared already; That wee call'd it the preſent Government, becauſe it is the onely Government ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Church by the Civil Power. But whether it be the Government by way of Eminency and <hi>jure divino,</hi> that was not the thing referred unto in the phraſe wee uſed. And as to the reſolving of your doubts and ſcruples, wee conceive it is here for us not material to go about the proving of the <hi>Jus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> of it; wee having proved, That it is the Government that is eſtabliſhed by the Civil Magiſtrate, and which doth lay as good a foundation to evidence the lawfulneſſe of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to it, as for the lawfulneſſe of your ſubmiſſion to the former Government, (and touching which wee ſuppoſe you were ſatisfied) your exceptions lying as much againſt the High-Commiſſioners, Chancellors, and Commiſſaries then, as they can do now againſt the office of Ruling Elders, and which is the chief thing wee apprehend is ſtumbled at in our Government.</p>
            <p>But yet if you deſire to have ſatisfaction given you touching that which wee are not aſhamed to profeſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Jus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> of the Presbyterian Government, wee referr you to what is ſo fully ſpoken touching this point, by ſundry learned Divines both of our own Church, and the Reformed Churches abroad, that wee know not, what can be added more <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>The Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> by London Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>The Provincial Synod of <hi>London</hi> their vindication of the Presbyterian Government. <hi>Rutherfords</hi> due right of Presbyteries. <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, by <hi>Gillaſpie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152166:32"/>And yet wee do not ſay, That there is no preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any Church or Aſſembly of Saints, but where our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and Government is erected intirely in all the parts of it, no more then wee ſhould deny him to be a man, in whom there were a defect of ſome integral parts, or in whom there were ſome ſuperfluous members. But as when Antichriſtianiſm ſo overſpread the face of the Church in thoſe dark times before the Reformation, God preſerved a Church, Miniſtery and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, though not without the mixture of many corruptions in doctrine and worſhip, even amongſt the Papiſts themſelves; So there was ſome of Chriſts Government and Diſcipline in the worſt times, though not intirely, nor without the mixture of much corruption in that Diſcipline and Government. And yet if you conſult Antiquity, you will not finde, that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Government hath lyen hid ſo long, as that for the ſpace of 1500 years it could never be found till this preſent. You have heard what rule did anciently belong to Presbyters, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that through the corruptions, that crept into the Church in after times, the exerciſe of that power was long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed. And the like may be ſaid of Ruling Elders, and as hath been ſhewed by others. But it is what <hi>de jure</hi> ought to be, and not what <hi>de facto</hi> is or hath been, which is that, which you and wee are chiefly to attend, and concerning which the Scripture muſt be the onely Judg, as wee have ſaid before.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, now ſubjection to our preſent Government is required by us; and then demand, <hi>Whether all that obſerve not our rank and order, and ſubject not themſelves to our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, muſt be taken for lawleſſe perſons? for ſo,</hi> ſay you, <hi>doth this cloſe connexion of ours ſeem to import;</hi> viz. <hi>Many who do not ſubject, but live, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here you do reaſon fallaciouſly <hi>à bene conjunctis ad male diviſa:</hi> For in our Paper wee ſpeak of ſuch, as did <hi>live in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and total neglect of the Lords Supper: That were ſcandalous and offenſive in their lives, drunkards, unclean perſons, and that will not ſubject themſelves to the preſent Government, but live as lawleſſe perſons.</hi> And therefore the lawleſſe perſons wee meant (and as might plainly have been gathered from our words) were ſuch, who as they ſubjected not themſelves to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152166:32"/>
of the Church, ſo they were alſo ſcandalous and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive in their lives, wee joyning theſe altogether, whom you divide. And whether ſuch as will neither ſubmit themſelves to the Laws of God, nor the Government, that is ſettled in the Church by the Civil Power, be not lawleſſe perſons, we leave it to you to judg.</p>
            <p>But yet we do here alſo minde you, That however we do not judg all thoſe to be lawleſſe perſons, that do out of conſcience not come up to the obſervation of all thoſe Rules, which are or ſhall be eſtabliſhed by Authority for regulating the outward worſhip of God, and Government of this Church (being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe blameleſſe) yet both you and wee may well remember, that ſuch as ſhould have refuſed to have ſubjected themſelves to the late Prelatical Government, would have been accounted in thoſe times to have been lawleſſe perſons.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>When wee make it an Order, that notice ſhall be taken of all perſons, that forſake the publick Aſſemblies of the Saints, you would gladly know, how farr wee extend this Saintſhip, this Church, and Aſſembly of Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which wee anſwer, as farr as the Apoſtle did, when wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> and the Churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> hee calls them <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Churches;</hi> notwithſtanding there were ſome in thoſe Churches that were leavened with unſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and groſly erroneous: In <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſome that denied the Reſurrection, made rents and ſchiſms, and ſundry groſly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: In the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſuch as mixed works with Faith in the point of Juſtification, and of which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would have thoſe Churches to take notice, even to the cenſuring of them, they being ſpots to thoſe Aſſemblies; and however Saints by profeſſion, and in regard of outward calling, being in Covenant with God, and having been baptized, yet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not their profeſſion by ſuitable converſation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, however there be ſundry of the like ſtamp in our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, wee do not therefore unchurch them, or make our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies not the Aſſemblies of Saints, becauſe of the corruption of ſuch members.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing our principles and practices are manifeſtly known to be utterly againſt the opinions and practices of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152166:33"/>
Donatiſts of old, and thoſe that have of late rent themſelves from our Churches, becauſe of the ſcandalouſneſſe of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt members, that are found in them, (though the ſin of theſe in our Churches is aggravated by giving that occaſion) you might well have ſpared your pains in tranſcribing out of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> what hee juſtly ſaid unto thoſe ſchiſmaticks, that hee had to deal with. Nay, you might rather have gathered from our Paper; That ſeeing wee ſaid, that notice ſhould be taken of all thoſe that ſhould forſake the publick Aſſemblies of the Saints, our purpoſe was to have cenſured ſuch as the Donatiſts were; That wee purpoſed to obſerve and cenſure thoſe that did main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and hold up private meetings in oppoſition to the publick; That crie down our Churches and publick Aſſemblies, Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Ordinances, (as you know ſeveral ſorts do; and who, as they hold ſundry groſſe errors, that ſubvert the faith, ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thoſe and other their practices, that in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do manifeſtly ſubvert the order, unity, and peace, that Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in his Church) do juſtly fall under Church cenſure, according to the rules of our Government above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And that therefore wee were not altogether ſilent concerning either the ſin or puniſhment of ſuch, as did err groſly in doctrinals or in diſcipline, ſo as to make ſuch dangerous rents from the Church, as the fore-named Sectaries do: Contrary to what you ſay of us in your Paper. And further, by ſuch as forſake the publick Aſſemblies of the Saints, of whom wee ſaid notice ſhould be taken, you might have gathered our mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was, that ſuch (of which ſort there are but too many amongſt us) who out of a principle of careleſneſſe, ſloth, worldlineſſe or manifeſt prophaneneſſe, do on the Lords day either idle out the time, or elſe are worſe imployed, when they ſhould reſort to the publick Aſſemblies: and who, as they are no friends to any private meetings for the good of their ſouls, in the uſe of any private means of conference or prayer for that end: So they do alſo Atheiſtically turn their backs on all the publick Ordinances, forſaking them and the Aſſemblies, where theſe are diſpenſed, ſhould be taken notice of in order to cenſure, if there was not reformation; and to neither of which ſort of perſons any indulgence is granted by any Laws of the Land, that wee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152166:33"/>
know of. And if you had gathered thus much from our Paper, as your miſtake had been far the leſs, ſo your Charity had been the more, then to have reckoned us in the number of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were. And yet we did not mean, That we intended to take notice in order unto cenſure of ſuch, who being ſound in the faith, and godly in life (though differing from us in point of Diſcipline and Government) had their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Aſſemblies from ours, they indeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace: They not being cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable by the rules of our Government, as is manifeſt, by what we have declared before. Although we remember, how all that ſubmitted not to the former Government, were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſchiſmatical. Neither did we reckon theſe in the number of the lawleſs Perſons, we ſpeak of, who ſubjected not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to our Government, and whom we account to be parts of the univerſal viſible Church militant here on earth, however they have alſo their publique Aſſemblies diſtinct from ours, though ſundry of them, as there is occaſion, reſort to ours alſo. But how we ſhould hereupon make either theſe or the lawleſs Perſons, that we ſpeak of, members of the inviſible Triumphant Church (all which we have reckoned to belong to the viſible) they muſt have eyes quicker then Eagles, that can diſcern how this follows, and therefore there is no fear our Charity ſhould ſo far over-reach, as you ſuppoſed it might.</p>
            <p>But ſtill you are unſatisfied; For you know not, it ſeems, what we mean by the word <hi>(Publique) the publique Aſſemblies of the Saints.</hi> By our profeſſions and practiſes in our owning the publique Aſſemblies, and where the publique Ordinances of the Word, Sacraments, and Prayer are diſpenced, which we our ſelves do conſtantly frequent and ſtir up others to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent alſo, it was plain enough, what we meant by publique Aſſemblies. And we are heartily ſorry, that you underſtanding our meaning, as is clear by what you ſay anon, ſhould by this but make your way to give a laſh at our <hi>Private meetings,</hi> which are none of them ſuch, as we need to be aſhamed of. And which, when we meet, either for conference about matters of Religion, or to pray together, and humble our ſelves for our own ſins and the ſins of theſe times; When there is not the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152166:34"/>
of a publique Aſſemby; or when perſonal or Family occaſions call for a private, is ſurely as commendable, at the leaſt, as a private meeting upon domeſtical, civil, or political occaſions: and therefore not to be ſecretly girded at. And on the other hand, we do not meddle with the cenſuring of thoſe, who being godly and ſound in the faith, in the main points of Religion, do yet differ from us in judgement, in matters of Diſcipline and Government: And have their Aſſemblies for Gods publique worſhip diſtinct from ours, as we are barred from it by the rules of our Government, as we have often ſaid before. And therefore we leave room enough for Conſciences that are truely tender. Though we cannot ſay ſo much for the Prelatical Government.</p>
            <p>Neither do we tranſgreſs any Laws of the Land which have made no proviſion to except any Perſons, that we meddle with, and are made cenſurable by the rules laid down in the form of Church Government, nor have we <hi>under Colour of Authority made any Laws and Edicts,</hi> but according to that power, that the civil Authority hath committed to us, have onely openly given notice in our ſeveral Congregations, of what offences are cenſurable by the rules of our Government, that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders might take heed, they incurre not that cenſure of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which Authority hath awarranted us to inflict upon the obſtinate and otherwiſe incorrigible. And therefore (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to execute what we are appointed to do by the civil power be to contemn it) we cannot be thought to have done any thing in contempt of the civil power, as it is not our ignorance of the Laws in force (that, we are confident, being grounded in reaſon fight not one againſt another, and which is your more charitable and favourable conſtruction) that hath led us into any practiſes, that are tranſgreſſions of them. And therefore though you much queſtion (upon what account ſoever it be, that we have been led into what we have acted) and think it concernes us to look to it, <hi>whether we have not run our ſelves</hi> into a premunire. Yet we are aſſured, we are as ſufficiently ſecured againſt that danger, as all the Juſtices in the Land are, that have acted upon other Ordinances of Parliament, which they have judged to be in force, as we do alſo thoſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152166:34"/>
to be, that have been the ground of our proceedings.</p>
            <p>But you have yet further to except, for whereas we ſaid, <hi>That like notice ſhould be taken of all ſcandalous Perſons.</hi> Your next Quaere is, <hi>Whether thoſe, that forſake the publique Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Saints in the ſecond order, may not be taken for ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Perſons comprehended in the third order?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we perceive you underſtood, who were meant by thoſe, that did forſake the publique Aſſemblies of the Saints, <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe who forſaking the Aſſemblies, where the publique Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances were diſpenſed, were upon that account really and indeed ſcandalous, and ſo being comprehended under the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of that expreſſion, might juſtly merit to be cenſured as ſcandalous Perſons. And thus conceiving you were not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet we, who were to expreſs our ſelves popularly, and ſo as we might be underſtood, conſidering ſome of that ſtamp, though they forſook the publique Aſſemblies of the Saints, and conſtantly turned their backs as on the Lords Supper, ſo on all other Ordinances, yet if not drunkards and ſwearers, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did not take themſelves to be ſcandalous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Do not think, that in this we are any more to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by you (we uſing variety of expreſſions onely for this end, that we might be better underſtood) then we blame Lawyers and Attorneys, and wherein we judge them not to be blame worthy) for uſing variety of expreſſions and Multiplicity of <hi>Synonnymous</hi> Words to make the matter more clearand out of doubt, where yet one and the ſame thing is underſtood by all.</p>
            <p>But now hereupon your complaint is; <hi>That we burden you with Traditions in multiplying of orders</hi> fine neceſſitate ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thritim uſque; <hi>and cry out,</hi> Quare oneramini ritibus? <hi>And tell us of lengthning out our Paper, which yet is not by theſe few words hereuſed made very much longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if you had remembred the multitude of Canons and burthenſom Ceremonies, that were rigorouſly preſſed, even to the higheſt cenſure in Caſe of refuſall, and under the burthen whereof ſundry truely conſcientious Perſons under the late Prelacy did ſigh and groan: When thoſe, that were ſcandalous enough in their lives, eſcaped cenſure (and which ſome have cauſe not ſo ſoon to forget) we think you would have ſeen lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
